<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A learned treatise concerning wards and liveries written by the Right Honourable and learned gentleman St. James Ley, Knight and Baronet, Earle of Marlebrough ...</title>
            <author>Marlborough, James Ley, Earl of, 1618-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 113 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51987</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M687</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1067</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12771211</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12771211</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93669</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51987)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93669)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 361:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A learned treatise concerning wards and liveries written by the Right Honourable and learned gentleman St. James Ley, Knight and Baronet, Earle of Marlebrough ...</title>
                  <author>Marlborough, James Ley, Earl of, 1618-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15], 79 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Bishop and R. White for Henry Shepheard and Henry Twyford ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Land tenure --  Law and legislation --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93669:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93669:1"/>
            <p>A LEARNED TREATISE <hi>CONCERNING</hi> WARDS <hi>AND</hi> LIVERIES; <hi>WRITTEN</hi> By the Right Honourable and learned Gentleman S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>James Ley</hi> Knight and Baronet, Earle of Marlebrough, Lord high Treaſurer of England, when he was Atturney of his Majeſties Court of WARDS and LIVERIES.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN IS SET FORTH the learning concerning Wards and Liveries, col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected and well digeſted out of the yeare-bookes, and other authorities of the Law, for the benefit of all that are Studious.</p>
            <p>London printed by <hi>G. Biſhop,</hi> and <hi>R. White,</hi> for <hi>Henry Shepheard,</hi> and <hi>Henry Twyford,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Bible in Chancery-Lane, and at the three Daggers in Fleete-ſtreete. 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:93669:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93669:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE DEDICATORY.</head>
            <head type="sub">TO THE STUDENTS OF the Common Law of England.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Is not to commend this Work, that this is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, for that it will it ſelfe; nor is it to preſent unto the curious Readers view, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velties but ancient learning uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly digeſted; the common Law of <hi>England</hi> that is defined to be <hi>Lex non Scripta,</hi> is beſt knowne by the multitudes of particular caſes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported and ſet downe in the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall yeare-bookes, and other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports
<pb facs="tcp:93669:3"/>of the Law, and in them the ſeverall reſolutions of different na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures being ſet downe as in time they hapned to be argued, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having regard to report toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all ſuch caſes as concerned one kinde of learning, breeds ſuch confuſion, that the painefull ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent muſt be very carefull under his ſeverall titles in his common-place-bookes to take notes with reference to the bookes from whence he takes them proper to be applied to the title under which he writes it, and likewiſe careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to coate his bookes to each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or otherwiſe upon ſundry occaſions hee may be driven to tumble up and downe the ſeverall bookes to reſolve himſelfe, and miſſe too of ſuch good reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as the bookes would afford him, if his memorie (which may eaſily faile) be not admirable;
<pb facs="tcp:93669:3"/>This ſmall Epitomie will-prevent that trouble, and helpe (more then any abridgment extant) the labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Student to know and find out the learning concerning wards, and Liveries, no ſmall part of our Law, nor eaſieſt learning; It was written by the right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and learned Sir <hi>James Ley,</hi> Earle of <hi>Marlebrough,</hi> Lord High Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> when hee was Atturney of the Wards and Liveries, for his owne private uſe, but now preſented to publike view for the common good of the Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of the Law; The learning concerning Wards and Liveries was not practiſed in one peculiar Court, nor differences concerning Wards lands not confined to any particular Court, but left to be proceeded in all Courts proper for the nature of the cauſes, till of late yeares: but now by a Statute
<pb facs="tcp:93669:4"/>made 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 46. A peculiar Court knowne by the name of the Court of Wards is erected, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in all things that concerne the Kings Wards is heard and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, ſo that now the Law as to Wards being to be onely practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed there: This Treatiſe will be of good uſe to him that intends that practiſe, for in it will be found ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much of the learning concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Wards, for him that deſires the knowledge of ſuch learning: It was chiefely publiſhed, and to him is wiſht encreaſe of Learning,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="instructions">
            <pb facs="tcp:93669:4"/>
            <head>Inſtructions for our M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. of our Wards and Liveries, for the better authorizing and <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting of him in the execution of his</hi> Office and performance of our ſervice.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt our pleaſure is, and we doe declare the Maſter of our Wards ſhall and may ſurvey and diſpoſe of all and every of our Wards, Idiots and Lunatiques, and reſpectively, of their Lands, Tenements, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditaments, Chattells, goods, properties, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, rights, titles, Intruſions, Arrerages and Meane-rates, and all Liveries, <hi>Ouſter le maines,</hi> and ancient Mannors, and all Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowſons, and preſentations of Churches, Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots, Reliefes, Coppyholds, Woods, Mines, and Quarries, of any our Wards, and of all duties belonging, or to belong to us by reaſon of any Tenure.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:93669:5"/>
            <p>That the Maſter of the Wards ſhall from time to time call unto him one or more of ſuch perſons as we nominate to be his aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, and ſhall uſe the aſſiſtance and advice of the mor one of them, at a place certaine, and times certaine be limited and appointed by the Maſter for the ſitting upon the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters within his ſurvey and diſpoſition, ſo that our Tenants and Suitors may make their repaire thereunto.</p>
            <p>That the Maſter with the advice afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid ſhall have power and authoritie to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound for the Wardſhips, Idiots, Lunatiques, and other duties aforeſaid, and to aſſeſſe all Fines, inſtall all payments for the matters aforeſaid, and to take Bond and Securitie in our name for the ſame, and to commit them to the ſafe cuſtody of our Clerke of our Wards, and Liveries to our uſe, and upon full payment to cauſe the ſame to bee deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered up and cancelled, and alſo to diſcharge and renew any Bond or Securities as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions ſhall require.</p>
            <p>That there bee ordained a ſpeciall ſeale for our Wards, Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eries, and Tenures, and for our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>iſing by reaſon thereof, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhall be in the cuſtody of the ſaid, Maſter of the Wards, and that no other ſeale
<pb facs="tcp:93669:5"/>ſhall bee uſed for, or concerning any the matters or cauſes aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>That the Maſter with the advice afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid ſhall have power and authoritie to grant Wardſhips for Fines, to make Leaſes of Wards Lands, and of Lands in our hands for want of Livery or <hi>Ouſter le maine,</hi> for Fines and reſerving of rents, and to grant the cuſtody of Idiots, and Lunatiques, and their goods and Lands, and to compound for meane rates, and to mitigate and remit as well the forfeitures of ſuch bondes and meane rates, as alſo to allow reaſonable recompence to proſecutors, ſuch as doe ſervice in the caſes aforeſaid. That the Maſtor with the advice aforeſaid ſhall have power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to give direction to any of our Courts, and unto the officers thereof and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any of our Miniſters and officers, as well for the proceedings and proſecution of any ſuites, and pleas, and finding of offices and inquiſitions, making of certificates and other ſervices, as alſo for the ſtay, ſurceaſing or ſuperſeding thereof, and that no direction ſhall be given to the contrary or otherwiſe by any of our chiefe Officers touching the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes: That all petitions or ſuites made to us touching the cauſes aforeſaid ſhall be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:93669:6"/>referred or directed to the ſaid Maſter, who ſhall have power with the advice afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid to anſwer and determine the ſame, and that petition, ſuite, or information ſhall not be received by our councell of revenew touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the premiſſes but that the ſame ſhall bee made and belong unto the Maſter of the Wards and Liveries.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Kings moſt excellent Majeſtie by Indenture bearing date <hi>10.</hi> Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuarij <hi>14.</hi> Jacobi, made betweene his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie on the one part, and Sir <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> Knight, Lord virulam, and Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour of England, Sir <hi>John Daccombe</hi> Knight deceaſed, <hi>Thomas Murrey</hi> Eſquire our Secretary, Sir <hi>James Fullerton</hi> Knight, one of the Gentlemen of our Bedchamber, <hi>John Walter</hi> Eſquire our Atturney Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, and <hi>Thomas Trevor</hi> Eſquire our Sollicitor Generall of the other partie, hath demiſed and granted unto them for our one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſe and benefit of ſundry Lordſhips, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Burroughes, Townes, Manners, Lands, Tenements, Liberties, Franchiſes and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditaments, to have and to hold the ſame from the Feaſt of <hi>St. Michael</hi> the Archan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell laſt paſt before the date hereof, for the tearme of <hi>99.</hi> yeares. And upon the truſt
<pb facs="tcp:93669:6"/>and confidence, and to the intent and purpoſe in the ſame Indenture mentioned and expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Now our pleaſure is that the ſaid Lord Chancellor and the reſt of the ſurviving Leſſees and their Aſſignes ſhall from time to time joyne in all ſuch grants, diſcharges, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyances and Inſtruments touching the matters aforeſaid by writing under their hands and ſeales and otherwiſe, as by the Maſter of our Wards, with the advice afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid ſhall from time to time be directed; And our further pleaſure is that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners for our revenewes (if neede ſhall ſo require) ſhall allow and give warrant in writing for the ſame.</p>
            <p>That the Maſter with the advice afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid ſhall have power by Letters Patents under our great Seale to appoint ſuch Feoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Eſcheators Auditors, Receivers, Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyors and other Miniſters of the Wards, Liveries, and matters aforeſaid as he ſhall thinke needfull for our profit, and ſervice, and from time to time to alter, change, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine and diſcharge all or any of the ſaid Officers and Miniſters, and their Offices and imployments as now or hereafter ſhall bee, and determine our Will and Pleaſure concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſame.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:93669:7"/>
            <p>That all Ordinances, Conſtitutions, Acts, made, publiſhed, declared and ſet downe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the hinderances of theſe our inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, ſhall ſo farre onely as they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, or to the hinderance thereof be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly voide and annihilated, any other matter, cauſe, or thing to the comrary thereof not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding.</p>
            <p>That the Maſter of our Wards and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries doe acquaint the Atturney and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of the Kings Majeſties Court of Wards and Liveries withall ſuch proceedings as may require their aſſiſtance for our ſaid Tenures, Revenew and profit, and eſpecially his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Atturney of that Court, and the Clerke of that Court for the preparing, clearing, finding, ſearching, and revealing of Tenures, and of the ſtates ſubject unto our Wardſhips and Liveries, by any due and lawfull meanes whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, whereas the Kings moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Majeſtie hath by his Letters Pattents under his great Seale, dated the <hi>11.</hi> day of this December granted unto the Maſter and Councell of the Court of Wards and Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Commiſſion with inſtructions and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for compounding for Wards, Idiots, and Lunatiques. Our will and pleaſure is,
<pb facs="tcp:93669:7"/>that the Maſter of the Wards ſhall diligently and carefully informe himſelfe of the ſame inſtructions and directions, and by Example and preſidents thereof order and diſpoſe the affaires of our Wards, Idiots, Lunatiques, Liveries and Tenures, ſo farre forth as the ſame may ſtand with congruitie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordancy, taking ſpeciall care that our juſt and reaſonable profits may be raiſed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diverting the ſame to others; and that nevertheleſſe our Tenants may be moderate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charged, and our Wards may be educated in Religion.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Examinatur per Jac. Ley.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:93669:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93669:8"/>
            <head>Tenures.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the King grant Land in Fee, and reſerve nothing,<note place="margin">Coo. 6. Whee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers caſe. fo. 6. b. Coo. 9. Ant. Lowes caſe. 123. 7. E. 4.12. b. 44. E. 3.45. a. Co. 9. Ant. Lowes caſe 123. b.</note> the Patentee ſhall hold by Knights ſervice <hi>in Capite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So if in his grant the King ſaies by expreſſe words, <hi>Abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> aliquo inde redendo,</hi> yet becauſe all Land muſt be holden by ſome ſervice, the beſt ſhall be intended for the King; therefore againſt the expreſſe words of the Patent, the Law will create a new Tenure by Knights Service <hi>In Capite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So if the King gives Lands <hi>tenend.</hi> as freely as he holds the Crowne, yet the Grantee ſhall hold by Knights ſervice <hi>in Capite,</hi> and in all theſe caſes the Tenure ſhall be by ſuch a part of a Knights Fee, as the value of the Land ſhall beare; what ſhall be ſaid of a Knights Fee, ſee the end of this Title.</p>
            <p>But if the Grant be <hi>Tenend. de nobis per
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93669:9"/>ſervitium unius Roſae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coo. 6. Whee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers caſe 7.</note> 
               <hi>Rubiae,</hi> or the like, <hi>pro omnibus aliis ſervitiis,</hi> this is a Tenure by Soccage <hi>in Capite,</hi> becauſe, if the King reſerve any ſpeciall rent, the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure ſhall be ſuch as he reſerves.</p>
            <p>If it be <hi>Tenendum de nobis ut de honore, Caſtrum vel Maner. de A. per ſervitium Militare,</hi> or, <hi>De honore Caſiro vel Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. de A. per ſervitium unius Roſae, Rubiae,</hi> or by 2. <abbr>s.</abbr> or by Fealty, for all the ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, theſe be meane Tenures of the King, in the firſt caſe common Knights ſervice; in the ſecond, common Soccage, becauſe the Tenure is not immediatly from the perſon of the King.</p>
            <p>But yet there are certain Honours ſo anciently annexed to the Crown,<note place="margin">33. H. 6. Br. Tenur 94. Inſt. fo. 77. a.</note> 
               <hi>(viz.)</hi> Barkinſteed, Newland, Rawleighe, The Abbey of Marle, &amp;c. That a Tenure of the King, as of any of theſe, makes a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure <hi>in Capite,</hi> either in Knights ſervice, or Soccage,<note place="margin">Stamf. pre. Rs.</note> according to the words of the Tenure; but yet this is improperly a Tenure <hi>in Capite,</hi> for he which holds of the King, as of any of theſe Honours, may alien without licence of the King,<note place="margin">44. E. 3.45.</note> which he cannot doe which holds <hi>in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite</hi> of the King, as of his perſon.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93669:9"/>
            <p>If the King grant Lands <hi>Tenend. de no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis per ſervitia debita,</hi>
               <note place="margin">44. E. 3.45.</note> This ſhall be <hi>in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite</hi> by Knights ſervice, becauſe where the words be uncertaine, the beſt ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for the King.</p>
            <p>If the King have Lands in his hands, holden by a common perſon immediatly as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>For Treaſon all Tenures, aſwell of the King as others, are thereby extinguiſhed,<note place="margin">Co. 6. p. Sir <hi>John Mollins</hi> caſe 6.</note> but if the King grant the ſame Land to another <hi>Tenend. de capital. Domino per ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitia debita,</hi> the Tenure is reſtored, and the Land holden of the Lord of whom it was holden before the Treaſon, and not of the King immediatly;<note place="margin">Co. 9. p. Bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leyes caſe 131.</note> yet if he grant it, <hi>Tenend. de nobis heredibus &amp; ſucceſſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus noſtris, &amp; al. capital. dominis feodi illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us per ſervitia debita,</hi> It ſhall not make an immediate Tenure from the King, but the immediate Tenure ſhall be of the Lord of whom the Land was holden be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and if he grant it <hi>Tenend. de nobis &amp;</hi> by new ſervices, <hi>&amp; faciend alias dominis ſervitiad bita,</hi> the meane Tenure ſhall be revived, without any regard of the prio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the words of the Patent, reſerving new ſervices. And this in favour of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93669:10"/>an ancient Tenure, but it is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the Creation of a new Tenure by the Kings grant, without any reſpect to an ancient.</p>
            <p>And in this laſt caſe,<note place="margin">Stam. praerog. Rs. cap. 12.</note> and alſo where the King purchaſeth land holden of a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject (in which caſe alſo all Tenures are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct) it hath alwayes been uſed upon a grant thereof made by the King to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the ancient Tenure of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, and if a grant had beene made o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, hee of whom the lands were holden before, had his remedy by petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the King.</p>
            <p>If the King purchaſe a Mannor, of which <hi>I. S.</hi> holds, hee ſhall hold as hee held before, and ſhall not ſue Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, nor pay Primer ſeiſin, nor hold <hi>in Capite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To hold of the King by graund Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geancy, is Knights ſervice <hi>in Capite;</hi> by petty Sergeancy, is Soccage <hi>in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite;</hi> whereof more in the following Title.</p>
            <p>To hold of the King by Caſtle-guard,<note place="margin">Lit. 34. b. Coo. 2 p. Cromwels caſe. 81. Lit. 266.</note> is Knights ſervice <hi>in Capite,</hi> but to hold by certaine Rent for Caſtle-guard, is but Soccage; But by <hi>Fitz Harberts natura
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93669:10"/>brevium</hi> a Tenure of the King,<note place="margin">Coo. 4. Luttr. caſe. 88. b. F. N. B. 256. a. Stam. praerog. 29. b.</note> as of an ancient Honour by certaine rent for the keeping of Dover C ſtle, is taken to bee Knights ſervice <hi>in Capite;</hi> but this ſeemes no Law.</p>
            <p>Note that there muſt of neceſſity bee a Tenure of all Lands in the hands of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects,<note place="margin">Coo. 9. p. Ant. Lowes caſe. 123.</note> wherefore if the King grants or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſes the ſervice of his Tenant by Knights ſervice, &amp;c. to his Tenant and his heires, this cannot extinguiſh the Tenure wholly, but that fealty ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine for neceſſity of Tenure;<note place="margin">26. H. 8.9.</note> As in graunts, ſo in offices found after the death of the Kings Tenant to entitle the King or Lord of a Wardſhip, the words of the office directs what the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure is, and therefore before the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of 2. <hi>E.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. if an office had beene found, that one held of the King generally, <hi>Sed per quae ſervitia Iurat. ignorant,</hi> this was taken for a Tenure by Knights ſervice <hi>in Capite,</hi> becauſe where the Tenure is uncertaine, the beſt ſhall be intended for the King.</p>
            <p>And for the ſame reaſon an office find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>De quo tenetur Iurator ignorant,</hi> this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93669:11"/>was taken for Tenure by Knights ſervice <hi>in Capite,</hi> becauſe where the Tenure is uncertaine, the beſt ſhall be intended for the King.</p>
            <p>And for the ſame reaſon an office find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>de quo tenetur jurat Ignorant.</hi> was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for the immediate Tenure of the King, and was ſufficient to entitle the King to a Wardſhip, but by the ſaid Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute it is provided that in the firſt caſe,<note place="margin">Stat. 1. Ed. 6.4.</note> it ſhall not be holden for a Tenure <hi>in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite,</hi> and in the ſecond place no immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Tenure of the King, but in ſuch caſe a <hi>Melius inquirendum</hi> ſhall be awarded, howbeit, if upon the <hi>Melius inquirendum</hi> the ſame be ſo again uncertainly found, the beſt ſhall be intended for the King, <hi>(viz.)</hi> a Tenure <hi>in Capite</hi> by Knights ſervice.</p>
            <p>There are alſo Tenures by colluſion, or eſtoppell,<note place="margin">7. E. 3.37.</note> as when a man ſeiſed in Fee ſimple of Lands holden of a common perſon, hath ſued a Livery, or Ouſter le main of the ſame out of the Kings hands, or hath confeſſed by any matter of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord a Tenure in chiefe of the King, this makes the Land holden of the King, of whemſoever it was holden before, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93669:11"/>the King ſhall have wardſhip by reaſon of this Tenure.</p>
            <p>Tenant in tayle generall holds of his Donor in ſuch Knights ſervice as hee holds Ouſter of his Lord,<note place="margin">38. E. 3.7. 2. Ed. 4.5. 1. Ed. 2. <hi>de mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus,</hi> Nevell.</note> yea although upon the gift made the Land be given <hi>Tenend. de capital. dom.</hi> yet ſuch a cauſe ſhall not alter the Tenure, but that hee ſhall ſtill hold of his Donor.</p>
            <p>Twelve plough Land, being every one of them anciently of the yearely va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of five nobles, make a Knights Fee, worth <hi>per ann.</hi> 20. <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr>
               </hi> which was anciently accompted ſufficient maintenance for a Knight, thirteene Knights Fees, and a third part being 400. markes yearely va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, made a Barony,<note place="margin">Re. 9.124. Ant. Lowes caſe. Inſt. fo. 69. a.b.</note> twenty Knights Fee of 400. <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr>
               </hi> yearely value, made an Earle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and according to the ſame propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion 800. markes a Marqueſdome, and 800. <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr>
               </hi> a Dukedome, the fourth part of which is paid the King for a reliefe, <hi>viz.</hi> of a Knights fee, 5. <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr>
               </hi> and ſo of the reſt.</p>
            <p>To hold of the King in Fee Farme,<note place="margin">Mag. Cart. cap. 27. 20. E. le caſe. <hi>Inhabitant de Saſſron Walden.</hi>
               </note> is a Soccage Tenure, and yet this Tenure ſhall yeeld no reliefe, becauſe the Law intends that the Farme, or Rent, that hee payes for the Land, is the full value of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93669:12"/>the land, and recompences all other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of the Tenure, and this is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon experience of the Exchequer.</p>
            <p>Tenures for the moſt part are either Knights ſervice, or Soccage; Knights ſervice is either <hi>in Capite</hi> of the King, or in common Knights ſervice; <hi>in Capite,</hi> is of two kindes, one more ſpeciall, <hi>viz.</hi> a grand Sergeancy, the other the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſervice; Knights ſervice is either of the King, as of ſome Honour, Caſtle, or Mannor, or Knights ſervice of common perſons: So Soccage is either <hi>in Capite,</hi> or common Soccage, <hi>in Capite</hi> more ſpeciall, as petty Sergeancy, or more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, the common Soccage is either of the King, as of ſome Honour, Caſtle, or Mannor, which are ſpecies of ancient Demeſne and Burgage of the King, or Soccage of a common perſon.</p>
            <p>There are alſo other Tenures, as Frankallmoigne, Tenure by Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, baſe Tenure, as Coppy-holder, Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure by villenage, of which I need not ſpeake for the purpoſe in hand.</p>
            <p>Of Knights ſervice and Soccage Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure of a common perſon: I may like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſpare the deſcription; but of either
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93669:12"/>of theſe much is ſaid in the Title of Wards colluſion, and thoſe that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Tenure <hi>in Capite</hi> by Knights ſervice.</head>
            <p>IS properly where lands are holden of the perſon of the King and of his Crowne, as of a ſeigniory it ſelfe in groſſe,<note place="margin">30. H. 8. Dyer 44. a.</note> and chiefe above all other ſeigniories; Improperly of him as of ſome ancient Honour annexed to the Crowne, as Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kingſteed, Newland, Rawleigh,<note place="margin">Stat. praerog. Rs. fo. 29. b.</note> the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey of Marle, &amp;c. And this deſcription is underſtood as well of Knights ſervice, as Soccage <hi>in Capite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Knights ſervice <hi>in Capite</hi> is denoted ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by expreſſe words, as <hi>Tenend. de no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis per ſervitium militare,</hi> or improperly, by conſtruction of Law upon uncertaine words, as in the caſes <hi>ſupra</hi> Title, Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nures.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:93669:13"/>
            <p>The more ſpeciall Knights ſervice, is grand Sergeancy,<note place="margin">Lit. 34. b.</note> which is denoted by ſome particular ſervice to be done in his own perſon to the King, then the other requireth, as to carry the Kings Banner, Launce, &amp;c. to lead his Hoaſt, to be his Marſhall, to carry his Sword before him at his Coronation, to be his Sewer, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, or Butler at his Coronation, to bee one of the Chamberlaines of his Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, and divers other the like.</p>
            <p>To Knights ſervice <hi>in Capite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2.24. Ed. 3.47. C. Stam. prero. Rs. fo. 7. <hi>ib.</hi> 6. L. 2. <hi>ib.</hi> 12.6.5. Plo. Com. Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gags. 17. 2. 13. H. 4.6. b. 22. H. 8. 5. E. 4.12. Stam. prerog. Rs. fo. 8.</note> are inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent not only Ward, Marriage, Primer ſeiſin, Reliefe, Livery, and Licence to alien, but alſo Prerogative to Wardſhips, and Primer ſeiſin of all other Lands hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en of common perſons in Knights ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, or in Soccage, and of all other ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, whereof the Tenant <hi>in Capite</hi> dyed ſole ſeiſed in Fee, and Fee taile in his owne Right, or in the Right of his wife in Poſſeſſion, Reverſion, Remainder, or in Right which deſcended to the Kings Ward, and not to any other cuſtomary heire,<note place="margin">12. Ed. 4.18.</note> as the younger ſons in Gavell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindes, &amp;c. Except the Lands holden of the Archbiſhop of Canterbury, the Biſhop of Dureſme between Tyne and Teſe, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93669:13"/>the Lords of the Marches, where the Kings writs runneth not, which they had in <hi>Anno</hi> 17. <hi>Ed.</hi> 2.<note place="margin">17. Ed. 2. Meues caſe. 133. Sta. 17. Ed. 2. Stam. pre. Rs. 7. b. 6. H. 2. Gard. 105.</note> But the body is not wherefore the King ſhall have that againſt all men, but the King ſhall have no Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative in the Lands of the ſecond Ward, which he hath by reaſon of Ward, as where one that held of the Kings Ward, was never ſeiſed of thoſe Lands, nor of the ſervice they were holden by.</p>
            <p>And the meane Lords, whoſe Fees the King hath in Ward by his Prerogative, ſhall have their Rents by which ſuch Lands were holden during the Minority payed to them, by the Kings Officers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to receive the profits of the Land holden of the other Lord, upon requeſt and tender of an Acquittance to the ſaid Officers.</p>
            <p>As by this Tenure the King hath Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative in caſe of Ward, ſo alſo he hath the like Prerogative of Primer ſeiſin, which ſee after, Title Seiſin.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:93669:14"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Soccage</hi> in Capite.</head>
            <p>THE Tenure is deſcribed in the laſt Title;<note place="margin">Coo. 6. p. Wheelers caſe 7.</note> the ſervice that this Tenure is knowne by, is generally where the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant holds by certaine ſervices, not by knights ſervice, for all manner of ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as <hi>Tenend. de nobis per fidelitatem tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> or by homage and Fealty, or by Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty and rent, or by homage, fealty and rent, or by a red Roſe, or the like, <hi>pro om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus ſervitiis,</hi> and although in the laſt example nothing be ſaid of Fealty,<note place="margin">Lit. fo. 36. a.</note> yet it is implyed by the Law, as incident to all manner of ſervices,; More ſpeciall ſoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cage <hi>in Capite</hi> is petty Sergeancy, which is where a man is bound by his Tenure to render yearely to the King a Bow, a Sword, Gauntlet, or ſuch like ſmall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter touching the War.</p>
            <p>To Soccage <hi>in Capite</hi> are incident,<note place="margin">Stam. praer. Rs. cap. 3. fo. 13. b.</note> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, Primer ſeiſin, and Livery, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to alien; whereof in theſe ſmall Titles.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:93669:14"/>
            <head>Common Knights ſervice of the King.</head>
            <p>IT is where land is holden of the King, as of ſome Honour, Caſtle, or Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, <hi>per ſervitium militar.</hi> expreſly, or implyedly by conſtruction of Law upon ambiguous words.</p>
            <p>This Tenure gives the King Ward, Marriage, Reliefe, Livery, but no Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſeiſin, nor licence to alien, nor hath the King hereby any prerogative to have other lands holden by the Kings Tenant of common perſons into Wardſhip. But yet the King ſhall by his prerogative have the Mariage of ſuch Ward of whom ſoever he holdeth beſides,<note place="margin">Stam. praer. Rs. fo. 10. 24. Ed. 3.31.6.5.</note> though his Tenant were enfeoffed of the lands hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en of his Maieſty after he was enfeoffed of his lands holden of others, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the priority of feoffement, which alwayes prevailes amongſt meane Lords; whereof more fully afterwards, in Title Marriage.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:93669:15"/>
            <head>Common Soccage of the King.</head>
            <p>IS where Land is holden of the King, as of ſome Honour, Caſtle, or Mannor, by the ſervices mentioned <hi>ſupra</hi> Title Soccage <hi>in Capite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Tenure yeelds a Reliefe, but no Wardſhip to the King, Marriage, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſeiſin, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Ward.</head>
            <p>THe Tenure by Knights ſervice, had his originall Creation for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Kingdome,<note place="margin">Lit. fo. 20.</note> binding the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to ſerve the King, or other Lord to whom he is Tenant in the Kings warres for a certain time, to the quantity of his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93669:15"/>Terme, and therefore that the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth ſhould not be unſerved, the Law gives the King,<note place="margin">Lit. fo. 22.</note> or the other Lord cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the heire Male of ſuch Tcnant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under age of one and twenty yeares at the death of his Anceſtor, together with the profits of his Land, till the ſame age.</p>
            <p>And of the heire Female,<note place="margin">Lit. fo. 22.</note> under the age of fourteen yeares at the death of her Anceſtor, and unmarryed, together with the profits of her Land, untill her age of ſixteen, to the end that he may provide himſelf of a man able to doe him Knights ſervice: But if the heire Female be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed at the death of her Anceſtor, then her Land only ſhall be in Ward but till her age of fourteen yeares, becauſe thoſe two yeares after fourteen, are given only to make tender of her marriage, which is already done: And if at her Anceſtors death ſhe be fourteen yeares old,<note place="margin">Lit. fo. 22. Bro. Gard. 86. Ac. 35. H. 6.52.</note> then there ſhall be no Wardſhip, neither of her body nor Lands, becauſe at that age ſhee may have a husband able to doe Knights ſervice, and that is her full age to be out of the Ward by the Common Law,<note place="margin">35. H. 6.54.</note> and the other two yeares are given in favour of the Lord.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:93669:16"/>
            <p>But when lands that are holden of the king or other Lord, deſcend to an heire male or female in the life of the father, from ſome other anceſtor, as from the grandfather &amp;c. of the mothers ſide, the mother being dead,<note place="margin">Lit. fo. 25. Coo. 3. Ratch. caſe. 38. Coo. 6. Re. Ambroſia: Gorges caſe. 22.22.6. re. N. B 143. o. Lit. fo. 114.</note> though the Lord ſhall have the Wardſhip of the land, yet the law of nature gives the father the Wardſhip of the body of ſuch heire, with this difference, in caſe of an heire female, that he ſhall have the Wardſhip of her body till he have a ſon, and then the Lord ſhall have it, becauſe by the birth of the ſon, he is become heire apparent, and this priviledge is given to the Father, but for his heire apparent, which now ſhe is not, in thoſe caſes the grandfather ſhall not have the Wardſhip of his grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>childe if his father be dead, touching the kings prerogative, to have Wardſhips of his lands, that his Tenant by knights ſervice <hi>in Capite</hi> held of another Lord: See before, Title Tenure <hi>in Capite</hi> by knights ſervice, and more in <hi>Stamf.</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the kings prerogative, <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>So the eſſence of Wardſhips is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, that the Tenant die ſole ſeiſed of lands in poſſeſſion, Remainder, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93669:16"/>or in right holden in knights ſervice, and a deſcent to their heire, for if men be joyntly ſeiſed in fee, or in fee tayle, and one of them die, his heire un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der age, he ſhall not be in Ward, becauſe the Lord hath his Tenant alive, <hi>viz.</hi> the Survivor who hath the whole, and by Title of Survivorſhip.</p>
            <p>And therefore if <hi>I. D.</hi> for money by him disburſed,<note place="margin">Coo. Knights caſe. 163.</note> purchaſe lands to himſelfe and others, and their heires, this is holden colluſion within the Statute, 34. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>ca.</hi> 5. to avoid Wardſhip which may accrewe after the death of <hi>I. D.</hi> becauſe he was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſole ſeiſed,<note place="margin">Coo. 9. Flopirs caſe. 126. a. b.</note> and ſo no title of Ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip could be after his death, becauſe of the Survivor.<note place="margin">Coo. 9. Flopirs caſe. 126. a. b.</note> But where to be joyntly ſeiſed of lands holden of the king in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, and not in remainder to them and the heires of the body of one of them, and he that hath the inheritance dyeth, his heire deins age, the king ſhall have the Wardſhip and Marriage of ſuch heire notwithſtanding the Survivorſhip of the other Tenant: And this is provided by the other Statute of 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8.17. in caſe of the king only, and therefore in ſuch caſe, if the lands were holden of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93669:17"/>perſon, there would be no wardſhip during all the life of the Survivor.</p>
            <p>Ward, where the Tenant dyeth ſeiſed of land in the very poſſeſſion thereof, by taking the profits, &amp;c. This admits no difficulty, and therefore in vaine to mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply caſes thereof.</p>
            <p>He in the Remainder upon an eſtate for life,<note place="margin">Coo. 2. Bing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams. 92. b. 33. H. 6.5. 24. Ed. 3.33. B. Na. Br. 142. b Coo. 2. Bing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams caſe. 92. b. Coo. 9. Quicks caſe. 129. b. Vet. Na. Br. Bro. Gard. 113. 4. H. 6.20. 20. Eliz. Dy. 362. a.</note> is not Tenant to the Lord untill the Remainder happen in poſſeſſion, and therefore if a man maketh a leaſe for life, the Remainder to another in fee, and he in the Remainder dies, his heire being within age, here during the life of the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for life, the heire of him in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder, ſhall not be in ward, becauſe the impediment is not removed; but in that caſe, if after the diſcent of the Remainder and before the death of the Tenant for life, the Lord grant away his Seigniory, and after the Tenant for life dies, the heire of him in Remainder being under age, neither the grantor nor the grantee of the Seigniory ſhall have him in ward.</p>
            <p>If the Tenant make a gift in tayle, the Remainder over in fee to another,<note place="margin">4. H. 6.10.</note> here the Tenant in tayle holds immediately of the chiefe Lord, and he die, his heire un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93669:17"/>age, he ſhall be in ward to the chiefe Lord, and ſo ſhall the heire of him in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder in fee, if the Tenant in tayle die without iſſue during the minority of the heire of him in the remainder, becauſe the impediment is removed by death.</p>
            <p>But if an eſtate tayle be made of lands holden of a common perſon, the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in fee to the King, the Tenant in taile die, his iſſue under age, he ſhall be ward to no body, becauſe the Tenure and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices are extinct by the fee ſimple, being in the King who can hold of none, And the eſtate of Tenant in tayle, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder over maketh both but one eſtate.</p>
            <p>If the Tenant make a leaſe for life,<note place="margin">Vid. Na. Br. B. Gard. 113.</note> or a gift in tayle, leaving the reverſion in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, he remaines Tenant ſtill to his Lord, and his heires ſhall be in Ward for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, becauſe his eſtate never moved at all out of him, and he is immediate Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; ſo note the diverſity betweene a Remainder and a Reverſion: So if the Tenant infeoffes <hi>A.</hi> who gives the land back againe in tayle to the tenant, or to the ſon of the tenant, <hi>Tenend. de Capital. Dom.</hi> yet the Tenant in tayle ſhould hold
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93669:18"/>of his Donor, and he of his Lord Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount, and the heire of the Donor ſhall be in Ward to his Lord, for the reverſion, and the heire of the tenant in tayle ſhall be in Ward to his Donor for the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion.</p>
            <p>And for the ſame reaſon,<note place="margin">Coo. 2. Bing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams Caſe. 92.</note> if the Tenant in tayle be with the reverſion expectant to himſelfe and his heires of lands holden by Knights ſervice, of a common perſon, and he dies, his heire within age, he ſhall be in Ward for his body, but not for his lands,<note place="margin">24. Ed. 3.33.</note> becauſe betweene the eſtate tayle, and the reverſion, ſtand two diſtinct e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates in the tenant, and the reverſion on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is holden immediatly from the Lord, and not the eſtate tayle in poſſeſſion; but if the Caſe had been Tenant in tayle, with the remainder to an eſtranger in fee, there the heire of the tenant in tayle under age ſhall be in Ward to the Lord of whom the land is holden, for body and land, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the particular eſtate and the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der make but one eſtate in Law, and all is holden of the Lord immediatly.</p>
            <p>But note, that in the Kings Caſe, if his Tenant make a gift in tayle, and grant the reverſion, over, or keepes the rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93669:18"/>expectant to himſelfe in fee, in theſe Caſes, and the like, by ſome bookes the King may elect his tenant, and there ſhall be a Wardſhip of the heire of the Tenant in tayle, or of him in the reverſion, as his Majeſty ſhall elect,<note place="margin">Stat. 34. H. 8. cap. 5.</note> and this election ſhall binde him, ſo that afterwards he cannot reſort to a new choice, but other bookes are contrary, <hi>viz.</hi> that he in the reverſion is only the Kings Tenant, and he hath no election but by common experience of the Court of Wards, they uſe to chooſe the Wardſhip of the beſt eſtate for the King, and for the third part to bee in Ward upon the Stat. of 32. &amp; 34. <hi>H.</hi> 8. of Wills, the words of 34. <hi>H.</hi> 8. are, that the King ſhall have as well lands in taile, as in fee ſimple.</p>
            <p>If the kings tenant,<note place="margin">F. N. B. 142. d. 14. H. 8.16.</note> or the tenant of a common perſon be diſſeiſed of his land, and die, ſo that a right only deſcend to the heire, yet the heires being within age, ſhall be in Ward for this right,<note place="margin">Coo. 3. Butler, &amp; Bakers caſe. 35. a.</note> becauſe after the diſſeiſin, the diſſeiſee remaines ſtill tenant to the Lord in right of Law.</p>
            <p>So if tenant in taile make a feoffement in fee,<note place="margin">48. Ed. 3.8. 15. Ed. 4.10. br.</note> and thereby diſcontinue the taile, and then dies, his iſſue under age ſhall
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93669:19"/>be in Ward to the Donor.</p>
            <p>So where the heire under age recovers lands holden, &amp;c. by a <hi>Br. de entrey ſur diſſeiſin,</hi> writ of Coſenage, for the action which deſcends he ſhall be in ward for this land ſo recovered, becauſe of the right deſcended to him. <hi>Mes auterment eſt lou il recover,</hi> by a writ which doth not deſcend as by a writ, <hi>De dum non fuit compos mentis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet where a poſſibility only deſcends, as if a man covenant with the father to ſtand ſeiſed to the uſe of the father and his heires upon a contingent, the father dies, his heire under age, the contingent happens, It was held by the Court of Wards, that the heire was in by deſcent, and that there ſhould be a wardſhip, and yet nothing deſcended but by a poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: And in every wardſhip there muſt be a deſcent,<note place="margin">Re. 10.83. a. Leonard Low. Caſe.</note> except it be in ſome caſes, upon the Statute <hi>de</hi> 32. &amp; 34. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>quem vide in le prochein.</hi> Title.</p>
            <p>Where,<note place="margin">Re. 3.62. a. Lincolne Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Caſe.</note> if the iſſue in tayle under age enters into the joynture of his mother by force of the Stat. 11. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 20. for a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture by her alienation thereof he ſhall not be in ward, becauſe he hath the land
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93669:19"/>in manner of a purchaſe, and not by deſcent.</p>
            <p>So if the father leaſeth to his ſon and heire for life, and dyeth,<note place="margin">9. Ed. 3.4.15. Co. 6. Sir Geo: Curſons ca. 76.</note> and the fee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends to the ſon under age, ſo that the freehold is mergd in the inheritance, yet he ſhall not be in ward for the land, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had the poſſeſſion by purchaſe, <hi>Si ſoit bona fide valet, ut &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And generally in all other caſes where the heire hath the land by purchaſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out colluſion, is where he buyes the land of his father <hi>(bona fide)</hi> and for valuable conſideration, or in the like caſes;<note place="margin">Coo. 10. Re. Leon. Lowes caſe. 83. b. t. Inſt. 78. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> for if it be by colluſion, then there will bee a wardſhip by the Stat. of Marleb. and 34. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. though the heire had not the land by deſcent, whereof after ſee in the Title Colluſion.</p>
            <p>If the King Knight the heire apparent of his owne Tenant,<note place="margin">Plo. Com. fo. 268. Ratclifts Caſe. Coo. 6. Sir Dru: Druries Caſe. 74. Coo. 8. Sir Hen. Conſtables Caſe. 171.2.</note> or of the tenant of a common perſon under age, and in life of his Anceſtor, hee ſhall not bee in ward though he be under age at the death of his Anceſtor, neither for body nor land, but ſhall for all purpoſes bee reputed of full age, becauſe the king by knighting him, hath adjudged him of full age, and able
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93669:20"/>to doe knights ſervice.</p>
            <p>But if he knight him after his Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors death while he is in ward,<note place="margin">Stat. Mag. Carta cap. 3.</note> hee is thereby preſently out of ward for his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but for his land ſhall be in ward till his full age of one and twenty yeares, <hi>Quem vide apres en le Title Marriage,</hi> as alſo ſome other Caſes, where the heire ſhall be out of wardſhip for his body, though his lands remaine ſtill in ward.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Wardſhips and Primer Seiſin.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>By theſe Statutes of</hi> 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>a.</hi> 34. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. of Wills.</head>
            <p>WHereas the words of the Statute are, That every perſon having Lands, Tenements, or Hereditaments of an eſtate in fee ſimple, <hi>per Knights ſervice in Capite</hi> of the King, or of any other Lord in common knights ſervice, &amp;c. May by his laſt Will in writing, by act executed in his life time, give, diſpoſe,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93669:20"/>will, or aſſigne two parts thereof for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of his wife, preferment of his children, or paying of his debts, &amp;c. leaving to the King wardſhip and primer ſeiſin, and to no other Lords wardſhip of ſo much of the ſame lands as ſhall amount to the cleare yearely value of a third part thereof; It is to be conſidered that theſe Statutes give to the tenant power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe his lands by his laſt will in eſcript, which he could not doe before theſe Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, which was ſome prejudice to the Lords of theſe lands for their wardſhips of the two parts ſo deviſed:<note place="margin">Coo. 6. Re. Sir Geo: Curſons Caſe. 76. a.</note> So then they doe give benefit to the King and other Lords, to have wardſhips, &amp;c. In caſes when they ſhall have had none before, though the Anceſtor neither dyed ſeiſed, nor any land deſcended to his heire, which are contrary to the rules of the Common Law, which ſee before in the laſt Title.</p>
            <p>And where the father conveyes his land holden, &amp;c. by act executed in his life time for advancement of his wife, preferment of his children, or payment of his debts, and dies, his heire under age, here is neither dying ſeiſed, nor deſcent;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93669:21"/>and yet the Statutes gives a third part of theſe lands to be in ward during the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nority of his heire, notwithſtanding it ſhall at his full age goe according to his fathers diſpoſition, becauſe the convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance was only avoided during the mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for benefit of Wards by the Statutes,<note place="margin">Co. Re. 8. Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies Ca. 165. b.</note> and not utterly void, but theſe Statutes doe in no caſe give wardſhip, where there is no heire, as where the father after ſuch conveyance is attainted of Treaſon, and dyed his iſſue, being under age, here the third part ſhall not be in ward by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute,<note place="margin">Re. 10.85. a. t. Leon. Lowes Caſe.</note> becauſe the Anceſtor dies without heire, in regard of a corruption of his blood.</p>
            <p>And note, where the Anceſtor devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth by his laſt will land holden, &amp;c. to his wife,<note place="margin">Dyer 150. b. St. 34. H. 8. ca. 5. Coo. 8. Sir Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Pexals Caſe. 85. a.</note> yonger children, &amp;c. the will is not avoided only, during the minority for the benefit of wardſhips, as in the ſaid Caſes of acts executed, but the will is ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly void for a third part by thoſe Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, and therefore he hath the third part by courſe of deſcent by the Common Law, and the will is good only for the other two parts, whereof there ſhall bee no wardſhip but only for the third part
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93669:21"/>deſcended, which the heire alſo ſhall have a ſon plein age, notwithſtanding the will,<note place="margin">Coo. 3. But. &amp; Bak. Caſe. 35.</note> for if a man deviſe a rent out of all the lands holden, &amp;c. this is void to charge a third part of the lands, notwithſtanding the land deſcends, charge of the rent.</p>
            <p>But where the land holden, &amp;c. are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeable <hi>per</hi> cuſtome in London, and ſome other townes, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e all may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed, and the will is not void for a third part, becauſe the land was deviſeable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Statutes which are in the affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and therefore doe not deſtroy the cuſtome, but the caſe: But the ſaying of theſe Statutes doe avoid the will <hi>pro tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coo. Re. 3.35. a. b. But. &amp; Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers Caſe.</note> and give a third part to the King for a wardſhip during the minority, &amp;c. And yet the heire is barred by cuſtome to have the third part at his full age, as before in the third caſe of diſpoſition by act execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted he is barred by the conveyance.</p>
            <p>It is ſeen who ſhall be ſaid to be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon having of lands, tenements, or here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditaments holden within the meaning of theſe Statutes, and that will beſt appeare by caſes of difficulty, for of common perſons having of lands, &amp;c. I purpoſe not to ſpeake, plaine matters need no
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93669:22"/>demonſtration, a diſſeiſed of land <hi>in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite</hi> which is put out of poſſeſſion, and hath only a right of lands,<note place="margin">Coo. 3. But. &amp; Bak. Caſe. 35. a.</note> holdeth of a common perſon Soccage lands, he is a perſon having of lands within theſe Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, becauſe in the judgement of the Law, he hath the land to many purpoſes, and therefore deviſe, &amp;c. by him of his other lands holden in Soccage, is good only for two parts, and his heire ſhall bee in ward, &amp;c. for the third part.</p>
            <p>If a man have only a fruitleſſe reverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on without rent expectant upon an eſtate tayle,<note place="margin">Coo. 11. Re. Henry Harpers Caſe. 24. Coo. 10. Leon. Lowes Ca. 80.</note> or for life of lands holden, &amp;c. and deviſe but two parts of his other lands holden in Soccage, a third part ſhall bee ſaved for wardſhips and primer ſeiſin, &amp;c. By theſe Statutes.</p>
            <p>But if the firſt grant away this reverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">Coo. Leonard Lowes Ca. 81.</note> then he may deviſe all his Soccage land, becauſe at the time of the deviſe, hee is no perſon having, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But if he that hath a remainder, &amp;c. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectant upon an eſtate taile, or a leaſe for life of lands holden, &amp;c. deviſeth all his Soccage lands, and dies before his remainder ſhall fall into poſſeſſion, this deviſe of all is good, becauſe he is not a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93669:22"/>perſon having of ſuch eſtate in lands hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, &amp;c. as by the common Law yeeldeth wardſhip, and therefore out of the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of the Statute, and ſo note the diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie betweene a reverſion and a remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der upon the Reaſon of the Caſes thereof before, Title Marier,</p>
            <p>Inheritances which of their nature are not of any certaine yearely value,<note place="margin">5. H. 7.36. Coo. 10 Leon. Lowes Caſe. 82. a.</note> as a Franchiſe to have felons goods, Court Leetes, waifes, eſtraies, advowſons, &amp;c. holden of the king, &amp;c. ſhall reſtraine the owner thereof to deviſe a third part of his Soccage land, becauſe he that hath theſe, is a perſon having hereditaments within the meaning of theſe ſttatutes.</p>
            <p>But where a man hath Soccage land,<note place="margin">Cars Caſe. 29. Eliz. cited in Coo. 3. But. &amp; Bak. Caſe. 30. b. a.</note> and hath alſo a rent hat was holden by knights ſervice <hi>in Capite</hi> extinguiſt in his Tenancy, he may deviſe or diſpoſe of it by act executed, all his Soccage lands, and there ſhall be no wardſhip of a tierce part, becauſe that the rent being extinct, he was not a perſon having thereof at the making of his laſt will, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>So where the husband and the wife be both Jointenants of an eſtate in Fee after coverture,<note place="margin">Coo. ibid. Stat. 34. H. 8.</note> the husband ſhall not be ſaid a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93669:23"/>perſon having of this land,<note place="margin">Coo. 8. Re. Wights. fo. 163. b.</note> becauſe hee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone is not owner of this land, and ſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, he that ſhall be ſaid a perſon, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of land holden, &amp;c. to be within theſe ſtatutes, muſt be ſole ſeiſed, and not joyntly with another.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, as theſe words are in theſe ſtatutes having lands, doe import ſole ownerſhip of the land holden,<note place="margin">Coo. 10. Leon. Low. Ca. 82. b.</note> ſo they doe alſo import and appoint the time of ſuch ownerſhip to be the ſame inſtance when hee makes diſpoſition or deviſe of theſe lands, ſo that the time of having, holding and diſpoſing ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre, where if a man convey to his yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, or to his wife, &amp;c. his lands holden, &amp;c. in Fee ſimple,<note place="margin">Coo. 11. Re. Harpers Caſe. 24. a.</note> either abſolutely, or with power of Revocation, having a third part, which is Soccage land to diſcend, and after purchaſe more land holden in Soccage, he may deviſe all his new pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed lands, becauſe at the making of his will, he had no land holden, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>So if a man have Soccage land, and convey it as Joynture to his wife, &amp;c. and afterwards purchaſed lands holden,<note place="margin">Coo. 10. Leon. Low. Ca. 83. b.</note> &amp;c. and deviſe two parts thereof and dieth, his heire under age, no part of the Soc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cage
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93669:23"/>land ſhall be taken to make a third part of the whole for watdſhip, &amp;c. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe when he made the conveyance of the Soccage lands he had no lands hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and therefore the conveyance good for the whole.</p>
            <p>But if a man having ſoccage land of 20. li. yearely value, deviſeth it to his yonger children, or to a ſtranger, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards purchaſeth land holden of the yearely value of 20. li. and dieth, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe is not good for all the ſoccage land, becauſe the VVill tooke not effect before his death, and before the land holden, &amp;c. See now the difference betweene the laſt Caſe of conveyance by Act executed, and this of deviſe.</p>
            <p>But if a man having land holden in Fee, and ſoccage land,<note place="margin">Coo. 3. But. &amp; Bak. Caſe.</note> deviſeth this ſoccage land, and after hee aliens his his land <hi>(bona fide)</hi> this diviſe is good for all the ſoccage land,<note place="margin">Coo. 10. Re. Leon. Lowes Caſe. 84. a. t.</note> becauſe when the VVill tooke effect, he had no land holden to cauſe a wardſhip or Primer ſeiſin.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it is to be conſidered, who ſhall be ſaid to be a wife or a child to be within theſe Statutes to be advanced, and then what eſtate ſhall be ſaid an advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſuch wife or children.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:93669:24"/>
            <p>A diſpoſition for the advancement that a man intend to marry,<note place="margin">Coo. 8. Virgill Parkers Caſe. 173. b.</note> though at the time ſhe be no wife, if after he marry her, ſhe is made a wife within the intent of theſe Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, as if at the diſpoſition made ſhe had had him.</p>
            <p>If by Act a man diſpoſeth of all his lands holden to his baſtard,<note place="margin">14. El. Dyer 313. b. Coo. 10. Leon. Lowes Caſe. 83. a. t. Coo. 6. Report, Sir George Curſons Caſe. 77. a.</note> or to one of his collaterall blood, not being his heire apparent, or to his grandchild in the life of the father, theſe Statutes give no wardſhip nor Primer ſeiſin of a third part, no more than if the depoſition had been to a meere ſtranger, bacauſe theſe are not children in judgement of law, and then the convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance remaines as it was, at the common Law, good to all, becauſe the Statutes provide for wardſhips, or primer ſeiſin, but where the conveyance is made to a childe.</p>
            <p>But if after the fathers death, the grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father conveieth the land to the uſe of any of his children, there ſhall be wardſhip, &amp;c. for a third part, becauſe by the fathers death the care of the children is caſt upon the grandfather by the law, as of his owne children, and therefore they are to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken children within the ſtatute.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:93669:24"/>
            <p>Then to ſee what ſhall be ſaid an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of ſuch wife and children; if the land conveighed to the wife and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by the ſaid father or grandfather, be levied to her &amp; her husband to her uſe, of the wifes lands, therefore there ſhall be no third part in ward,<note place="margin">Coo. 9. Floyers Caſe. 126.</note> becauſe this conveyance is no advantage to her in regard the land was originally hers, and moved not from her husband, &amp; therfore out of the ſtatute.</p>
            <p>So if a man convey land to his wife for life, the remainder for one of his ſons, the remainder is no advancement to the ſonne, to give wardſhip either for the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy or third part of the land by theſe ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Coo. 2. Binghams caſe. 94.</note> becauſe the mother is the Kings te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant during her life by advancement, and ſuch a remainder which may give ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of body and land at the Common Law, is onely intended, by the word Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder in theſe Statutes, which this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder doth not; the reaſon is about the title of the ward.</p>
            <p>But a remainder which is in part of a reverſion,<note place="margin">Coo. 10. Leon. Lowes ca. 81. a.</note> as if a man makes a leaſe for life or yeares, and after grants the rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for life or in taile <hi>le remainder in fee</hi> to his ſonne, and after the grant for life, or
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:93669:25"/>Donee in tayle dies without iſſue, it ſhall be ſaid advancement within theſe Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, and ſhall give cauſe of wardſhip of the body during the life of the tenant for life, becauſe this remainder by common Law,<note place="margin">Coo. 9. Holts Caſe. 132. b. t.</note> ſhall draw ward and marriage; as alſo a revorſion doth in ſuch caſe give wardſhip, becauſe he in reverſion is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate tenant to the Lord, and not te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in tayle, or for life.</p>
            <p>If the ſon and heire, or any other ſon purchaſe land of his father <hi>(bona fide)</hi> for money, &amp;c. this is no preferment for the childe within theſe meaning of theſe Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, and therefore there ſhall bee no third part of theſe lands taken for ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or primer ſeiſin, becauſe it was land purchaſed by the childe, and not given by the father to prefer him.</p>
            <p>This Statute gives authority <hi>disjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve</hi> to make a diſpoſition either by act ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted, or by will of two parts of land holden, &amp;c. And thereupon if a man by act executed in his life time, diſpoſe of two parts for the advancement of his wife,<note place="margin">Coo. 3. But. &amp; Bakers Caſe.</note> and preferment of his children, and payment of his debts, he cannot deviſe the third part thereof, becauſe he had
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93669:25"/>executed his authority before, but if hee had aliened two parts to a ſtranger <hi>(bona fide)</hi> then he might alſo deviſe two parts of the third part remaining, becauſe his alienation to a ſtranger is out of theſe Statutes.</p>
            <p>If a man alien two parts for advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his wife,<note place="margin">Re. 6.18. Sir Edw. Cleres Caſe.</note> &amp;c. he may alſo make a feoffement of the third part to a ſtranger, or he may make a feoffement of the third part to the uſe of his laſt will, and by his will may declare the uſe of that feoffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to a ſtranger.</p>
            <p>But here note that the land paſſeth by feoffement, and not by will, and that the will ſerved but as a limitation of the uſe upon the feoffement, and yet in that caſe, a third part of the two parts firſt diſpoſed of ſhall be in ward.</p>
            <p>If a man by act executed conveyes two parts for life in taile for advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his wife,<note place="margin">35. El. Clem. Howards Caſe cited in Coo. 10. Re. Leon. Lowes Caſe. 81. a.</note> &amp;c. he may alſo deviſe the reverſion of the ſame two parts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Statute gives him full power over the two parts, to diſpoſe it as he will, by will or otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>It is to be obſerved, that theſe Statutes are to be expounded to ſave a third part
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:93669:26"/>for wardſhip and primer ſeiſin, when the advancement continues in the advanced without alteration either by deſcent, or alienation, and not otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Wherefore,<note place="margin">Coo. 2. Bing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams Caſe. 93. b. 94. a. Coo. 9. Holts Caſe. 132. a.</note> if the ſon advanced aliens <hi>(bona fide)</hi> or dies, and the land deſcends to his heire in the life of the father that gave the land, there ſhall be no wardſhip of a third part by theſe Statutes; the ſame law is, when the land is conveyed for the advancement of the wife, or pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the debts.</p>
            <p>Whereas theſe Statutes ſerve to be in ward,<note place="margin">Coo. Re. 10. Leon. Lowes Caſe. 84. a. m.</note> &amp;c. lands to the full yearely va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of a third part of the whole, it is to be noted that the ſame value ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted as the lands be of value at the Anceſtors death.</p>
            <p>The thing of a caſuall and uncertaine value may not be left for the third part,<note place="margin">Coo. Leon. Lowes Caſe. 81. a. t. R. 3.32. b. But. &amp; Bak. Caſe.</note> as a franchiſe to have felons goods, and of fugitives, and out of fines, outlawes fines, amerciaments, which have not been accuſtomably let unto farme for yearely rent, but if they have been ſo let, then they may be left for the third part.</p>
            <p>The King or the Lord ought to have his third part immediatly after the death
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:93669:26"/>of the tenant,<note place="margin">But. &amp; Bakers Caſe. 34.</note> and ſhall not expect upon any uncertainty, wherefore if a man ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of three acres holden <hi>in Capite,</hi> &amp;c. leaſeth one acre for life, and after deviſeth the other two acres, and dyes, and after the tenant for life dies, yet the deviſe is void for a third part of the two parts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the third part did not deſcend im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to the heire.</p>
            <p>In conſtruction of theſe Statutes,<note place="margin">35. H. 8. Bro. Teſtaments 29.</note> an equality hath been uſed, ſo that for the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying and making up of a third part ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by theſe Statutes, parties alike in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſed ſhall equally and alike be reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, wherefore if a man have three ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Mannors holden of three ſeverall Lords by Knights ſervice,<note place="margin">Coo. 8. Virgill Parkers Caſe. 173. b.</note> every Mannor being of equall value, he cannot deviſe two Mannors, and leave the third to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend according to the generality of the words of theſe Statutes, for then he ſhould prejudice the other two Lords of their wardſhips, but he muſt deviſe two parts of every Mannor, and leave to deſcend a third part of every Mannor, to make a wardſhip to every Lord.</p>
            <p>So if a man ſeiſed of land holden,<note place="margin">Coo. Virgill Parker. 173. b.</note> &amp;c. diſpoſeth before mariage one moity for a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:93669:27"/>joynture of his wife that ſhall be, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter marriage diſpoſeth the other for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his debts and legacies, and the third part for the King, as other Lords ſhall be equally taken out of both halfes, and not out of the halfe laſt diſpoſed.</p>
            <p>So if the other deviſeth the land,<note place="margin">Coo. 9.133. b. Mat. Menes Caſe.</note> to his eldeſt ſon one part, and ſo to foure other ſons like parts, whereof one part only is holden, &amp;c. the third of the whole ſhall be made up equally out of every ſeverall third part of a younger brother a like quantity, if the King or the Lord hath once the benefit of the Statutes againſt one ſon, the Statutes are ſatisfied, and he can have no further benefit therof againſt another-ſon, as if the father convey land holden, &amp;c. to one ſon in tayle the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder over to another of his ſons in tayle or in fee,<note place="margin">Coo. 9. Tho. Holts Caſe. 132. a.</note> and after the fathers death the King or the Lord hath wardſhip and primer ſeiſin of a third part, and then the firſt ſon dyeth without iſſue, the King or Lord ſhall not have the benefit of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute againſt the ſon in the remainder, for the Statutes doe extend to the firſt ſon advanced only, if he ſurvive the father, and then be owner of the land.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:93669:27"/>
            <p>Wherefore, if a man have lands hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en,<note place="margin">20. El. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throps Caſe, cited in Coo. 3. Re. But. &amp; Bak. Ca. 31. a b</note> &amp;c. of the yearely value of 20. li. and Soccage lands of 10. li. yearely va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, he may deviſe all the lands holden, &amp;c. and leave the Soccage land only to deſcend for wardſhip and primer ſeiſin, and the Statutes are ſatisfied, and the heire ſhall ſue Livery for one of the acres holden, &amp;c. though no land be deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him, if the land be holden of the King by Knights ſervice <hi>in Capite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So if a man have land only holden,<note place="margin">Coo. 10. Leon. Lowes Caſe 84. b.</note> &amp;c. And conveyeth the whole for advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his wife, preferment of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and afterwards purchaſe ſo much land in Soccage as amounteth to the third part of the land holden, and leaves this to deſcend, this Statute is ſatisfied, and the conveyance is good for the whole land holden, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And note,<note place="margin">Coo. 10 Leon. Lowes Ca. 84.</note> that to make wardſhip upon theſe Statutes, the eſtate of the Lord holden, ought to continue after the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants death; And therefore if a man have an eſtate tayle only of land holden, and hath Soccage, and dyeth without iſſue, ſo that the eſtate tayle is ſpent, the deviſe is good for all the Soccage land, ſo if the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:93669:28"/>land holden be defeated by condition af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Tenants death.</p>
            <p>And ſo the eſtate of the Tenure ought to continue after the death of the Tenant;<note place="margin">Coo. 3. But. &amp; Bakers Caſe. 34. b.</note> wherefore if the King gives land to one, and his heires to hold during the life of the Patentee by Knights ſervice <hi>in Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te,</hi> and after his death in Soccage, or <hi>E converſo,</hi> here ſhall be no wardſhip or primer ſeiſin, neither by the common law, nor by theſe Statutes, becauſe in the firſt caſe the Tenure continues not after the Tenants death, and in the ſecond caſe, the Tenure to make a wardſhip commenceth in the ſon only.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Colluſion to avoid Wardſhips.</head>
            <p>IF Tenant enfeoffe his ſon and heire ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent,<note place="margin">St. Marle. b. ca. 6. Plo. Com.</note> or his collaterall heire appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, to make him have an eſtate in land as a purchaſor, and ſo to beguile the Lord of his wardſhip, becauſe the heire comes not to the land by deſcent; this is colluſion apparent, and maniſeſt againſt
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:93669:28"/>which by the Statute of Marleb. made <hi>Anno</hi> 32. <hi>H.</hi> 3. It was provided that the Lord ſhall notwithſtanding have the wardſhip of his heire.</p>
            <p>There is alſo colluſion which is not ſo manifeſt, as when the Tenant enfeoffes others upon colluſion between him and them had for the benefit of the heire, and to prevent his wardſhip, and this colluſion is averable, againſt which alſo this Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of Marleb. provideth.</p>
            <p>To inſtance in particular caſes what ſhall be ſaid, colluſion within theſe Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of <hi>Marleb.</hi> and what is not, is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, becauſe the caſes thereof are too many for this Treatiſe, as for that by the ſaid Statute of 34. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. a more ample proviſion is made againſt Collu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, then was by that former.</p>
            <p>Wherefore before the ſtatute of 34.<note place="margin">Inſt. fo. 78. a.</note> 
               <hi>H.</hi> 8. if the father had ſtept but a little fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and had made a Feoffement to his ſonne and heire, and to a ſtranger, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the inheritance were limited to the heires of his heire, and that the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger had but an eſtate for life.</p>
            <p>Or if the Father had made but an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate for life or taile to his ſonne and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:93669:29"/>heire,<note place="margin">27. H. 8.10.</note> and limited the remainder, and granted the Reverſion to another, or had left the Reverſion in himſelfe, or if the father had enfeoffed a ſtranger for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of his younger ſonnes or of his daughter, or for the paiment of his debts, and after doe enfeoffe his heire, in all theſe caſes the Lord had beene pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented of the wardſhip of his Tenants heire, and he not helped by the Statute of <hi>Marleb.</hi> becauſe thoſe conveyances were in judgement of the law no Colluſion, neither apparent, nor averable within the intent and meaning of the ſaid Statutes.</p>
            <p>But now by theſe Statutes of 32.<note place="margin">Coo. 6. Sir George Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons caſe. 76.</note> 
               <hi>H.</hi> 8. in all theſe caſes and the like, Colluſion may be averred for a third part of the Land ſo conveyed, and the conveyance <hi>pro tempore</hi> avoided,<note place="margin">Re. 8. Rep. Wignts caſe. 163. Inſt 78. a.</note> or the wardſhip, primer ſeſin, in caſe of land holden of a common perſon, and for wardſhip of primer ſeſin in caſe of land holden of the King for a third part of the land, but as theſe Statutes in many other caſes gives remedy to the King and other Lords, where they had none before; ſo in other caſes theſe Statutes give the Tenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſit, where he had none before.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:93669:29"/>
            <p>And therefore, where the King,<note place="margin">Coo. 8. Wights caſe. 3. 164. b. Coo. 10. Leon. Lowes caſe. 82, 83.</note> or the Lord by the Statute of <hi>Marleb.</hi> might take advantage by Colluſion apparent, or where the Tenant conveyes the land to his ſonne and heire under age, of an eſtate in fee ſimple, might have had the whole land ſo conveyed by fraud in ward, now by theſe Statutes, becauſe they did enable him to convey the two parts for prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his childe, the King ſhall have but a third part in ſuch caſe, this Statute of 34. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. concerning Colluſions to this purpoſe, that if the Tenant being ſeiſed of an eſtate of inheritance doe by Act executed in his life time, convey by covin to any perſon his land holden, &amp;c. for, or with divers Remainders over in Fee to a ſtranger, or to his owne right heires, or ſhall make by fraud contrary to this Act, any eſtate, conditions, meſnal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, tenures, or conveyances, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to defraud the King or the Lords of theſe wardſhips, &amp;c. which ought to come to them after their tenants death by force of this Statute, and of the Statute of 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. the ſaid eſtates and conveyances being found by Office to be ſo made by covin.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:93669:30"/>
            <p>There the King ſhall have the ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and other profits,<note place="margin">2. &amp; 3. Eliz. Dyer 193.</note> &amp;c. according to the intent of the ſaid Statute, as though no ſuch eſtates had beene made, untill the ſaid office be lawfully undone by tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe or otherwiſe, and other Lords ſhall have their remedy in ſuch caſes, as their wardſhips of body and lands by the Writ of Wards, and ſhall diſtraine and averre for their reliefes, heriots, or other profits, as if no ſuch eſtates had beene made.</p>
            <p>But obſerve,<note place="margin">10. Eliz. Dyer 276. Re. 8.165. a. Wights caſe.</note> that it is adjudged upon theſe Statutes of 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. and 34. <hi>H.</hi> 8. that where a third part is left out of ſuch conveyance to be in Ward, &amp;c. no covin or colluſion can be averred for the other two parts diſpoſed of by the Tenant, though the covin be found by Office, becauſe the intent of the ſaid Statute is, that the King, and other Lords ſhould be ſatisfied with a third part, which is here left unto him.</p>
            <p>If <hi>A.</hi> with his proper money purchaſe land holden, &amp;c. to himſelfe, and <hi>B.</hi> an Infant, and their heires, this cannot be averrred to be Colluſion to avoid ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Primer ſeſin after the death, within the intent of theſe Statutes, becauſe <hi>A.</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:93669:30"/>was never ſole ſeiſed as he ought to be by the proviſion of theſe Statutes, and no feoffment which <hi>A.</hi> can make of his moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie can be averred to be Colluſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if no feoffement were, no benefit of wardſhip could acrue <hi>perſon Mort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the ſonne and heire purchaſe <hi>(bona ſide)</hi> for money, his fathers lands holden,<note place="margin">Re. 10.83. b. Sir Nicholas Strange's caſe, cited in Leon. Lowes caſe.</note> &amp;c. this ſhall not be taken to be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance of Colluſion within the Statute of <hi>Marleb.</hi> nor within the Statute of 32. &amp; 34. <hi>H.</hi> 8. to have a third part to the King or other Lords for the wardſhip, becauſe by the third part it cannot be found preferment of him within the meaning of this Statute.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Marriage.</head>
            <p>THe Tenure of Knights ſervice as it gives the King or the Lord the ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the lands of the heire under age, ſo it gives him alſo the cuſtody of the body of the heire male till his age of 21. years, &amp; of the heire female, if ſhe be under the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:93669:31"/>age of 14. yeares, and unmarried at the death of her Anceſtor, till her age of 16. yeares, whereof ſee before <hi>Sect.</hi> 6.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Reliefe.</head>
            <p>INcident to all manner of Tenures,<note place="margin">14. H. 8.45. &amp; 156. Tenures. Br. Reliefes.</note> be they King or common perſon, except the Tenure of the King by Fee-farme, which therefore yeelds no Reliefe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Farme or rent thereof is in the judgement of the Law accompted a full value of the Land, except Tenures in <hi>Franke Allo moigne</hi> by divine ſervice, and the like.</p>
            <p>But Reliefe is no ſervice whereby the land is holden,<note place="margin">Co. 3. Penants caſe. fo. 66. Lit. fo. 28. b.</note> but a profit or approve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſervices, as a bloſſome falne from a tree, and it is due immediately upon the death of the Anceſtor.</p>
            <p>The Reaſon why it is payed, as alſo the name thereof is given by <hi>Brooke,</hi> thus, <hi>Cum homagio facta fuerit, &amp; fidelit. Succ. abillis cum plenitat. exiſtent. oportet ſtatim quod Tenem. quod fuit in manibus Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſoris,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:93669:31"/>&amp; haereditas qui jacens fuerit eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum deceſſum relevatur in manibus habend. &amp; propter talem Relevationem fasiend. orit ab heredibus preſtatio qui dicitur re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>levin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This excludes all purohaſers from pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reliefe, as hee ſaith alſo in another place, <hi>Dabit Relevin. qui ſuccedat juri hereditario, non qui acquiret,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Brac. fo. a. 11. H. 8.422. 22. Ed. 4. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe 8.</note> And with this agreeth the current of our bookes now at this day, and common experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and this alſo excludes inheritances which goe in ſucceſſion; and therefore all Corporations, becauſe they never die, ſo that their land deſcend not, pay no Reliefe,<note place="margin">Bro. Reliefe 9. 3. H. 4 2.</note> becauſe the ſucceſſor hath not the land, <hi>Jure hereditario,</hi> but by preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; a Corporation may pay no Reliefe, the heire ought to be of full age at the death of his Anceſtor, or elſe he is not to pay any Reliefe,<note place="margin">Lit. fo. 24. a. b. Mag. Cart. c. 3.</note> as appeareth by <hi>Br.</hi> and by all other bookes, and the full age for this purpoſe as of the heire male of Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant by Knights ſervice 15.21. of his heire female 14 as alſo of the heire of the Tenant in Soccoge his age of 14. hence it is plaine, that where the Lord hath the wardſhip of the heire of his Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:93669:32"/>that at the full age of the heire hee ſhall have no reliefe: And this is true, although the Lord hath only the land in ward, and not the body, whereof if the Lord hath by the priority the body and the land holden of himſelfe in ward, the other Lords by poſteriority at the full age of the heire, ſhall have no reliefe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had every of them the land holden of themſelves in ward.</p>
            <p>But where the heire is left under age, and the caſe is ſo,<note place="margin">Inſt. 83. b. Stam. prae. 96. 24. E. 3.14. Vet. Na. Br. 93. a.</note> that the Lords of whom the lands deſcend is holden, cannot have the land in Ward, there at the heires full age he ſhall pay reliefe to ſuch Lord; as where a man holds his land of the King by Knights ſervice <hi>in Capite,</hi> and of other Lords by Knights ſervice, and dies, his heire being under age, and the King ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the wardſhip, and all his lands which he holds of others, the heire at his full age is to pay reliefe to the other Lords, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had no lands in Ward.</p>
            <p>The reliefe for a Knights fee of lands holden by Knights ſervice <hi>in Capite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Inſt. 83. b. Lit. fo. 24. b s. 112. Coo. 7. Nevills caſe. 33. b. t.</note> is the fourth part of the value thereof, <hi>viz.</hi> 5. li. for a whole Knights fee, being anciently valued but at 20. li. <hi>per annum,</hi> And ſo
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:93669:32"/>after the ſame proportion for a greater and leſſer quantity; whereof ſee before in Tenures.</p>
            <p>Of land holden by grand Sergeancy,<note place="margin">Lit. fo. 35.</note> the reliefe payable to the King, is the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of the land by the yeare, above all charges and repriſes.</p>
            <p>The remedy for a ſubject to get his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, is to deſtraine for it,<note place="margin">7. H. 6.13. Inſt. 83. a.</note> if it be not had in the life of the Lord, his Executors re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy is an action of debt againſt the heire.</p>
            <p>In the Kings caſe, where reliefe is due to him, the uſe is in the writ of Livery, to the heire, and directed to the Eſcheator to command him to take ſurety of the heire for payment of the reliefe, but hee ſeldome or never doth the ſame: but them of the Exchequer to whom the charge in this kinde belongs upon record of the Livery, ſend out ſummons againſt the Tenant for the ſaid Reliefe, and upon the Sheriffes Return of <hi>Nihil, &amp;c.</hi> Proces of Extent for the ſame.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:93669:33"/>
            <head>Of Livery.</head>
            <p>IF after the death of the Kings Tenant <hi>in Capite,</hi> his heire enter into the land to him deſcended before he doth his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and hath received his ſeiſin from the King, he is by law an intruder upon the Kings poſſeſſion, and ſhall forfeit all the profits of ſuch lands to the King from the time of his intruſion, untill he have ſued out the Livery, and hath no free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of the land in him,<note place="margin">3. H. 7.2. Stam. prae. Rs. fo. 12.14. b.</note> inſomuch that he can neither make a feoffement, nor other diſpoſition thereof, nor ſhall his wife bee endowed thereof, but for reſtitution ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, and the profits thereof, he is driven to ſue to the King for his ſpeciall grace and pardon.</p>
            <p>To prevent which penalties, the Law requireth that the heire doe (at times) therefore by the Law appointed ſue to the King to have ſuch lands re-delivered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him by his highneſſe,<note place="margin">They cannot ſeize before the office.</note> which is called in Law, ſaving of Livery, till which be done,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:93669:33"/>the Eſcheator in the County where the land lies may (to the Kings uſe) ſeiſe and take the whole profits of the land,<note place="margin">Coo. 9. Sir Geo. Reinolds caſe. 95. b. Coo. 8. Hales Caſe. 172. b.</note> which notwithſtanding is not uſed to be done till office be found, and then the King is in poſſeſſion without ſeiſure, and is to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered of all profits ſince his Tenants death, till Livery ſued forth, then he doth his homage, and hath the land delivered unto him out of the Kings hands, and pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the King his Primer ſeiſin, whereof ſee before in the laſt Title.</p>
            <p>But becauſe to your ſuing of Livery many things are to be done with great care,<note place="margin">Coo. 8. Hales Caſe. 172. b.</note> and ſtill the Lord gives the heire 6.3. moneths time for the proſecuting thereof, if the heire at his full age, having been in Ward, or at the death of his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, if he after his full age tender his Livery, and purſue it with effect, he ſhall have as much benefit by his tender, as if he had done homage, and had ſued his Livery; And therefore if the heire after the tender dies within the ſaid 6.3. moneths,<note place="margin">Coo. 9. Holts Caſe. 132.</note> ſo that the proſecution of the Livery is become impoſſible by the act of God <hi>In providentia excuſat legem,</hi> and the intereſt of the King to Primer ſeiſin is
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:93669:34"/>determined, as if he had taken homage of the heire when he made his tender, but the meane rates if any were forfeited, are not diſcharged.</p>
            <p>And ſo for the ſame reaſon, the heire after ſuch tender may bargain and ſell, or make other diſpoſition of the land, and the ſame is good in law if he die within the ſaid 6. moneths,<note place="margin">Inſtructions by the new inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions the <hi>ſur veon.</hi>
               </note> and hath as much power over it, as if he had ſued his Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, this tender at 6. moneths end is uſed to be continued over for 6. more, and ſo from 6. moneths to 6. moneths, as long as the Maſter of the Wards ſhall give leave, and in the meane time the heire hath like benefit thereof, as if he had ſued his Livery.</p>
            <p>Livery ſhall not be ſued but where the Kings Tenant dyed ſeiſed of lands holden by Knights ſervice <hi>in Capite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Inſt. 77. a.</note> or Soccage <hi>in Capite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the Tenure be Knights ſervice <hi>in Capite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stat. Marleb. ca. 16. <hi>viz.</hi> F.N B. 61.</note> the King hath the ſame preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive for his Livery that he hath in caſe of Wardſhip, whereof ſee before to have a Livery ſued of lands holden by his Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of others, either by Knights ſervice, or Soccage, or for lands which he hath in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:93669:34"/>Ward by reaſon of Ward, or that are holden of his Tenants, or that are holden of a Biſhop by a Tenant that dyeth, while the temporalties of a Biſhoprick are in the Kings hands.</p>
            <p>But if the Tenure be in Soccage <hi>in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4. El. Dy. 113. F. N. B. 256. b. 32. H. 8 Br. Gard. 97. 45. E. 3.19. 35. H. 8.6.52. F.N B 259. Inſt. 77.</note> the King as he ſhall have primer ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin, and a Livery to be ſued of no other lands holden by his Tenant of others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the land holden by Soccage <hi>in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite;</hi> ſo alſo the heire of ſuch Tenant ſhall not ſue Livery, nor pay primer ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin, if at the death of his anceſtor he bee under the age of 14. but in every of theſe caſes, they to whom the body belongeth ſhall have an <hi>Ouſter le maine una cum exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus, viz.</hi> the Lord of whom the lands are holden by Knights ſervice.</p>
            <p>And here in the laſt caſe,<note place="margin">20. Eliz. Dyer 362.</note> howbeit when he attaines his full age of 14. yeares hee muſt ſue Livery, or elſe ſhall loſe the meane rates.</p>
            <p>But bee the heire of the Tenant by Knights ſervice <hi>in Capite</hi> under age at the death of his anceſtor,<note place="margin">Weſt. 1. cap. 22. St. 39 H 6. ca. 2. a. Stam. prae. Rs. 13.</note> yet at his full age he ſhall ſue Livery, although he hath been in Ward, as well as though he had been of full age at the death of his anceſtor,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:93669:35"/>though with ſome difference for the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſeiſin, as appears, Title Primer ſeiſin.</p>
            <p>The time after the death of the Kings Tenant for his heire to ſue Livery, is of lands in queſtion holden by Knights ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice <hi>in Capite,</hi> be the heire in Ward, and then comes to full age, or be of full age at his anceſtors death, then <hi>viz.</hi> the heire male at 21. the heire female above 14. at the death of the anceſtor, then if the poſſeſſion of the free-hold doe deſcend immediately after the anceſtors death to the heire, the Livery is to be ſued forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with: If only a reverſion doe deſcend, then not till after the death of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Tenant, if it be a reverſion without rent incident thereunto; howbeit the heire at this day hath election either to ſue immediately in the life of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Tenant, paving for Primer feiſin but halfe a yeares value, or to tarry till after his death,<note place="margin">Inſt. 77. a. Dyer 14. Eliz. 308. b.</note> and then to ſue it, and pay a whole yeares value of the land, but if it be in reverſion with a rent incident there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, and he ſueth out his Livery in the life of the Tenant, he may doe ſo, and ſhall pay for Primer ſeiſin but one yeares value of the rent.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:93669:35"/>
            <p>And the time of the heire of Tenant by Soccage in <hi>Capite</hi> to ſue Livery is,<note place="margin">Coo. 9. Hales caſe 132. b. Re. 9.81. Leon. Lowes caſe.</note> immediatly upon the death of the Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, with the ſame obſervation of poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, or Reverſion, as is for the heire of the Tenant by Knights ſervice <hi>in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite,</hi> if he be above 14. years of age at the death of his anceſtor, and if hee be under, then hee is to ſue no Livery till he be 21. yeares, as is afore ſhewed.</p>
            <p>But the time which the law hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for Soccage of Livery may by Accident be altered or changed,<note place="margin">Co. Re. 9.173. Sir Hen. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables caſe. Coo. Re. 6.74. Sir Dru Dru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries caſe.</note> as where the ſonne and heire is a Knight in the life of his father, and his father dies before he be of full age, his Livery muſt be ſued or tendred immediatly on his fathers death, and before his full age, becauſe the King by Knighting him, hath adjudged him of full age.</p>
            <p>So in <hi>diebus illis,</hi> if the father had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into Religion, his heire being of full age, his heire ſhould have ſued Livery preſently, and ſhould not have expected his fathers naturall death.</p>
            <p>No Livery can be ſued of lands above the yearely value of 5. li. before office found before the Eſchator or other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners<note place="margin">Stat. 33. H. 8. cap. 22. 14. Ed. 4.5.</note>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:93669:36"/>by vertue of the Kings Writ or Commiſſion derected out of the Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie or other Courts that have authority to make ſuch writs or Commiſſions for ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Livery.</p>
            <p>But Livery of lands under the yearely value of 5. li. may be by warrant made from the Court of Wards and Liveries be ſued forth,<note place="margin">St. 33. H. 8. c. 22</note> although there had been there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of no office returned.</p>
            <p>The reaſon of this is,<note place="margin">F.N.B. 253. <hi>Ib.</hi> in Stam. 52.</note> that the King may be certainely informed by matter of Record, who ſhall be his Tenant, and whom he ought to make Tenant, and this cannot be but upon an office, or by a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Writ or Commiſſion, in nature of that Writ or Commiſſion to enquire of all wards, or the like.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>And theſe Writs or Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are of two ſorts.</head>
               <p>Theſe of the firſt ſort are to enquire after the death of the Anceſtor of what lands holden of the King,<note place="margin">14. Ed. 4.5.</note> or of others, the Anceſtor was ſeiſed at the time of his death, the value, the day when he died, who is next heire, and of what age, of this
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:93669:36"/>kind are <hi>diem clauſ. extremum,</hi> which is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed within a year after the anceſtors death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Memorandum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Stam. prae. Rs. 52. F.N.B. 253. c.</note> if there be no ſuite made within the yeare after the anceſtors death, and upon theſe writs the Jury ought to enquire, who tooke the profits ſince his death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deneverunt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> whether the Anceſtor died in ward to the King.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Or Commiſſions of the nature of theſe Writs.</head>
               <p>Theſe of the ſecond ſort are ſuch as iſſue upon ſome defect in offices, and found upon the five firſt writs of this kind, are</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Qua plura,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">F.N.B. 255.</note> where ſome of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors lands are left out.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Melius inquirendum,</hi> Inquired upon ſome defect in the former office.</item>
               </list>
               <p>But if the heire were of full age at his Anceſtors death, and ſo found by office, then he ſhall have Livery upon that office without any eſtate <hi>probanda.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Datum eſt nobis intelligi,</hi> where after the delivery of the writ, and before office found before the Eſcheator dieth, or is removed from his place.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:93669:37"/>
               <p>But now theſe Writs or Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſince the erecting of the Court of Wards may paſſe out of the Chancery or other Courts having authority to make them,<note place="margin">Stat. 33. H. 8. cap. 22.</note> &amp; by warrant or bill ſigned and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by the Maſter Surveyor &amp; Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and receiver, of the Court of Wards, or one of them, directed to the chancellor of England or other chancellor or officer having power to award ſuch writs; if upon office found upon any of theſe writs, the heire be found under age, and in ward, &amp; after do accompliſh his full age,<note place="margin">F.N.B. 254. a. 257.</note> he muſt have a writ of Eſtate <hi>probanda,</hi> to prove himſelfe of full age before he ſhall have Livery.</p>
               <p>But if the Tenant be found within age,<note place="margin">13. H. 4.6.</note> &amp; in ward, and after his full age other lands deſcend to him, which the King ſeiſeth, by an office that finds the heire of full age, he muſt ſue an eſtate <hi>probanda</hi> by reaſon of that office which found him within age, which is the beſt Record for the King.</p>
               <p>If generall Livery, or <hi>Ouſter le maine</hi> be not rightly purſued according to the order of Law,<note place="margin">Stam. prae. Rs. 12. a. <hi>infra</hi> title Ouſter le main</note> the King may receive the land without any proceſſe and ſhall be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered of all the meane profits from the ſuing of the Livery.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:93669:37"/>
               <p>A livery is not rightly purſued according to the order of law when it is ſued by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells,<note place="margin">35. H. 6. Liv. 19</note> as if the heire ſue Livery but of part of that which is found by office, as where the Anceſtor had lands in ſeverall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, if the heire ſue a generall Livery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore office found in every county where he hath land, omitting them in the Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the Livery is void, and the King may have reliefe; whereof ſee a whole Title in <hi>Stamf. Praerog. Regis, fo.</hi> 8.6. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But in ſome caſe a Liverie may be ſued of parcell,<note place="margin">38. H. 6.9. a.</note> as where land diſcends to two daughters, one of the full age, the other under age, ſhee of the full age ſhall have the Livery with a partition ſutable of all things, and this Livery is well ſued, though it be not of all the land deſcended; but things not ſeverable, as advowſons, or the like, muſt ſtill remaine in the Kings hands till the other daughter be of full age.</p>
               <p>And note,<note place="margin">Stam. prae. Rs. ca. 5. fo. 22.</note> that between Coparceners the King upon the Livery alwayes makes partition, and this is for the Kings bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, in that upon partition every one ſhall have a part of the land holden <hi>in Capite,</hi> for if any of them ſhould have for her part the lands holden of others only, then
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:93669:38"/>the King ſhall loſe his prerogative in that part for ever; wherefore in the writ of Livery in ſuch caſe, there is a proviſo, that every of them ſhould have for part, parcell of the lands holden <hi>in Capite.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When two are found heires by one Title,<note place="margin">1. H. 7.28.</note> be they twins male, and found heire by the ſame office, divers men by ſeverall offices are found heires to the ſame anceſtor, and by the ſame title there, becauſe it is doubtfull to the King to whom to make a Livery, untill the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty and the verity be diſcuſt betweene them; then his highneſſe ought to make a Livery to him that is proved to bee the true heire to the common anceſtor; the manner of this triall is by Interpleader, and in what caſes it ſhall be, and in what not, you may ſee at large in <hi>Stamf. prae. Rs. fol.</hi> 51. 65. <hi>&amp;</hi> 66. <hi>b.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The manner of ſuing a generall Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry may be ſeen in <hi>N. B.</hi> 258. <hi>viz. Samf. prae. Rs.</hi> 79. 80. and for this purpoſe ſee alſo the Statute 33. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 22.</p>
               <p>But at this day generall Liveries are out of uſe,<note place="margin">Stam. prae. Rs. 67.2. Inſt. 77. a.</note> and for the moſt part men uſe to ſue ſpeciall Liveries, which contain in them a pardon for all entries, intruſions,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:93669:38"/>iſſues, profits, and likewiſe to diſpenſe with all miſuſings which may happen up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a generall Livery, &amp;c. But theſe bookes muſt be underſtood where the lands are found in the office to be above 20. li. yearely value, for otherwiſe gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Liveries are moſt in uſe.</p>
               <p>Thus ſpeak our books, but by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon experience of the Court of wards, and liveries ſince the Stat. of 33. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 2. are diſtinguiſht, and ſued in this manner, <hi>viz.</hi> A generall Livery under value, which is when the land whereof Livery is to be ſued, is found by the office not to exceed 5. li. <hi>per annum,</hi> and the leſſe fees are appointed by the ſaid Statute for the ſuing forth thereof.</p>
               <p>A generall Livery above value, <hi>viz.</hi> when the land is found by office to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 5. li. yearely value, and under twentie pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> and then grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fees are allowed by the ſaid Statute, and upon ſuing either of thoſe Liveries, no other Primer ſeiſin is payed then the meane profits of the lands, inured from the anceſtors death to the ſuing of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, according to the deſcription thereof by the Stat. <hi>Prae. Rs. cap.</hi> 3. See before
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:93669:39"/>Title Primer ſeiſin; which meane pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits may alſo be ſaved by tender of the Livery, and ſo the King hath nothing for Primer ſeiſin.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, a ſpeciall Livery which the Court of Wards ſayes ought not to bee ſued, unleſſe the land be above the yeare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly value of 20. li. found by office, and if a man will ſue a ſpeciall Livery for lands of a leſſe value, he muſt confeſſe his land to be above that value.</p>
               <p>Howbeit, the law is taken otherwiſe in our bookes, where mention is of a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Livery, without ſpeaking of the value of the land, and reaſon proves it may be ſo called, becauſe it containes a ſpeciall pardon of all entry, intruſions, meane rates, &amp;c. which may well be granted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a leſſer quantitie of lands, as upon a greater, and upon this ſpeciall Livery, no primer ſeſin other than the ſaid meane profits is taken by the name of a primer ſeiſin, but they uſe to take a ſum of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to the Kings uſe by the name of a fine for his Maieſties ſpeciall grace, and pardon vouchſafed to his Majeſties Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects by the faid ſpeciall liveries to be ſued of, and in poſſeſſion, and the heire hath
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:93669:39"/>not him in ward, or if the livery be ſo ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of, and in poſſeſſion, and the heire hath not beene in ward; or if the livery be to be ſued of a Reverſion halfe a yeares value, which agreeth by the common proportion above in the bookes, named primer ſeſin, and upon tender of any of theſe Liveries, they ſhall uſe to take a bond, for that ſhall be due to the King up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Livery ſued for feare of the heires death within ſixe moneths before the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſued out; and note, that a ſpeciall Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very gives the heire licence to enter and take the profits of the lands immediatly without ſuing any writ of <hi>aetate probanda,</hi> as if a Livery had been thereof ſued, and pardons all iſſues, meane rates and profits of the lands, but yet the ſame are paied before he can have ſuch li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very and pardons, all entries and entraſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by the heire, or any his Anceſtors, and fines for alienations without licence, and yet they of the Exchequer notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſuch Livety uſe to ſend proceſſe to the Sheriffe to ſeiſe the land after ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienation, and to compell the heire to pay a fine, and to ſue a pardon for ſuch alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation without licence, ſo that the benefit
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:93669:40"/>of a ſpeciall livery above a generall, as I conceive is little other than that the heire thereby avoids the trouble and charge of ſuing his writ <hi>de aetate probanda,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the danger of miſuſing his Livery, and by conſequence the reſeiſing of this land without great inconveniences, they appeare in part in this Title, and more amply, <hi>Praerog. Rs. fo.</hi> 19. 80, 81. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Ouſter le maine.</head>
               <p>Is in all other caſes where Liveries is not to be ſued, as where the Land is hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to be in common Knights Service of the King, as of ſome Honour, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, Caſtle, &amp;c. and the heire within age, no Livery ſhall be ſued; and yet becauſe no man may enter upon the Kings poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion without his leave, the heire at his full age ſhall ſue an <hi>Ouſter le main cum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itibus:</hi> but in the firſt yeare of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Inſt. fo. 77. a. 1. Eliz. Dyer 168. a.</note> it was queſtioned in the Court of Wards, whether it ſhould be a Livery <hi>Cum exitibus,</hi> or an <hi>Ouſter le maine,</hi> and there agreed, that <hi>Ouſter le maine</hi> is onely of Lands in the Kings hands holden of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers then of the King, but yet ordered,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:93669:40"/>that a Livery in this caſe <hi>una cum exitibus</hi> ſhould be granted by the name of <hi>Ouſter le maine,</hi> becauſe the courſe of that Court was ſo by the ſpace of 30. yeares before; where note, that no meane rates ſhall be forfeited for land holden of the King by common Knights ſervice, though there be no tander of Livery, which is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why <hi>Ouſter le maine</hi> is granted <hi>cum exitibus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So if the Eſcheator claime land by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of dying, &amp;c. before office,<note place="margin">Stat. de Eſche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. mode 29. E. 1.</note> and after by the office no title is found for the King, the partie that ought to have againe the land ſhall have an <hi>Ouſter le main cum exitibus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So if the Eſchetor will ſeiſe land found by office to be holden of the Archbiſhop of Canterbury, or of ſuch other perſon as are exempt in the firſt Chapter of the Statute <hi>deprae. Rs.</hi> they ſhall have an <hi>Ouſter le main cum exitibus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So of lands holdan <hi>in Capite,</hi> if a Leaſe be made for life the Remainder over to a ſtranger, and Tenant for life dies, this matter being found by Office, if the King ſeiſe the Land, he in the Ramainder ſhall have an <hi>Ouſter le main cum exitibus.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:93669:41"/>
               <p>So where two hold land joyntly of the King <hi>in Capite,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">F. N. B. 257. g.</note> and one dyeth, and the matter is found by office, which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the King ſeiſeth the land, the Survivor ſhall have an <hi>Ouſter le main cum exitibus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So if the heire of Tenant in Soccage <hi>in Capite</hi> be under the age of fourteene yeares at his anceſtors death,<note place="margin">35. H. 6.52. F. N. B. 256. c. Stam. prae. 12. b.</note> and the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is found by office, and yet the Eſchea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor ſeiſeth the land for a primer ſeiſin, <hi>le procheine de kinne</hi> to the heire, ſhall have an <hi>Ouſter le maine cum exitibus,</hi> but yet in that caſe after the 14. the Eſcheator may ſeiſe, and the heire muſt have Livery, and for want of tender thereof, he ſhall loſe meane rates from his age of 14.</p>
               <p>So if Tenant by Soccage <hi>in Capite</hi> die alſo ſeiſed of other lands holden of other Lords then of the King by Knights ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice or Soccage,<note place="margin">45. Ed. 3.19. a. 4. Eliz. Dyer 213.</note> which deſcend to the heire under age, and after office thereof found, the Eſcheator ſeiſeth the lands into the Kings hands, the Lord of whom the land is holden by Knights ſervice in the one caſe, and <hi>procheine kinne</hi> in the other caſe ſhall have the lands out of the Kings hands by <hi>Ouſter le maine cum exitibus;</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:93669:41"/>And if the heire be of full age at his Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors death he himſelfe in both caſes ſhall have the <hi>Ouſter le maine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And generally in all caſes whereupon the matter is diſcuſt,<note place="margin">Stam. prae. Rs. fo. 77.6. et 82. 21. <hi>H.</hi> 7.5. 29. Aſſ. 43.</note> it appeareth either upon the returne of the office, or upon <hi>trover monſtrous de droit ou petition de droit</hi> and the like, as the cauſe ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, that the King had no right or title to the thing he ſeiſed, there judgement is given that the Kings hands ſhall be amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and thereupon the writ of <hi>Amovcas manus</hi> or <hi>Ouſter le maine</hi> is awarded to the Eſcheator.</p>
               <p>By the Common Law the <hi>Ouſter le main</hi> was never awarded <hi>Vna cum exiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> though it did ſo plainely appeare that the King ought not to have ſeiſed,<note place="margin">Art. Sup Ca. 19. 29. Ed. 1. Statute de Eſcheator</note> but this was the helpe by two Statutes in the 28. and 29. yeares of King <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. by which was provided that where land is ſeiſed into the Kings hands without juſt cauſe the profit thereof in the meane time ſhall be wholly reſtored to him that ought to have had the land, and hath received the dammages upon <hi>Ouſter le main cum ixitibus.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:93669:42"/>
               <p>But if by the ſame Stat. of <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. it is provided that if after ſuch <hi>Ouſter le main cum exitibus,</hi> a title doth appeare for the King in Chancery, Kings Bench, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, &amp;c. whereby the King is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled of a title growne before the <hi>Ouſter le main,</hi> although the party could have had no <hi>Ouſter le maine</hi> if the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords had then appeared without avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, yet in that they did not then appeare, he ſhould not be now caſt out of poſſeſſion, without a <hi>Scire facias</hi> againſt him, upon which if he be warned, and doe not come, or commeth and ſay nothing againſt the Kings Title, the land ſhall be reſeiſed, and the King reſeiſed, &amp; the King anſwered of the profits from the time of the firſt office, though this Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute make no mention of Livery, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>Ouſter le maine;</hi> yet by equity Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries are taken to be within the meaning thereof; And here note this difference, that in the caſes laſt mentioned, no ſeiſin ſhall be before <hi>Scire facias,</hi> and againſt the party, yet in the caſe above, and Title Liveries; of a livery the King he may reſeiſe without office, whereof ſee at large Title Reſeiſor, in <hi>Stamf. prae. Rs.</hi> 856.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:93669:42"/>
            <head>Office.</head>
            <p>AN Office is an Inqueſt by twelve men at the leaſt, taken before the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheator, aſſiſted with the Feodry, or the Commiſſioners of things which convert the Kings revenue to finde his Title, and as a matter of Record, requiſite bv. law to give the King an actuall and perfect ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin, or poſſeſſion of the thing whereof the office is found, as of Eſcheators, Wards land forfeited or aliened without licence, and the like.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>To purſue which Deſcriptions.</head>
            <p>OFfices concerning Wardſhips,<note place="margin">4. Ed. 4.24. 33. H. 8. c. 22.</note> of which only I ſpeake, the Eſcheator may finde as well by office, as <hi>Virtute brevis,</hi> but with this difference,</p>
            <p>Added by Statute, that if the land
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:93669:43"/>whereof the office is to be found, bee of 60. pound yearly value or above, and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the King, the Eſcheator forfeits 5. pounds if hee finds any office thereof without the Kings writ directed to him for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Writs or commiſſion in nature hereof whereupon offices are to be found may not be made out of the Chancery or other Court having authority to make the ſame but by warrant or bill ſigned by the Mr. Survey or of the court of Wards,<note place="margin">33. <hi>H.</hi> 8. ca. 12.</note> or one of them directed to the Chancellour or offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer having power to award the ſame writs.</p>
            <p>Such or the Commiſſions are the <hi>diem clauſit extremum Mandamus devenerunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Co. 8. p. Stoughtons Caſe. 169.</note> 
               <hi>quae plura, Melius inquirendum &amp; datum nobis intelligi,</hi> the ſeverall natures whereof in what caſes they be, ſo ſee Title Livery.</p>
            <p>To which may be added that after the <hi>diem clauſit,</hi> or a <hi>mandamus</hi> awarded an office found, there ſhall goe forth no more writs of the ſame kind to enquire further therefore at the inſtance of the ſame party.</p>
            <p>But where the office is imperfectly found againſt the King, in ſuch caſe the King cannot traverſe the office, as a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject may upon ſurmiſe in the Court of Wards, that the lands are of greater value,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:93669:43"/>that they are holden of other ſervices, that the Tenant was ſeiſed of another eſtate, that theſe are more heires or other heires then were found in the firſt office, or where by the firſt office the heire was found within age, where indeed, the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant dyed without heire, ſo that the land ought to eſcheate, or where by the firſt office one is found heire of full age, where he was under age, and generally where his highneſſe hath a better Title then was found for him by the firſt office, a <hi>Melius inquirendum</hi> may bee awarded in the Kings behalfe.</p>
            <p>But in good diſcretion,<note place="margin">Co. 8. Paris Stoughtons caſe 169.</note> no <hi>Melius in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirendum</hi> ſhould be awarded after a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect office found againſt the King without view of ſome record or other pregnant matter to intitle the King.</p>
            <p>If upon the <hi>Melius inquirendum</hi> the office be found againſt the King,<note place="margin">Ibidem. 169. b.</note> he ſhall not have a ſecond <hi>Melius,</hi> but is found by the office even as a ſubject, as againſt whom his traverſe wch ſee Title Traverſe.</p>
            <p>And note that upon the laſt office upon the <hi>melius,</hi> makes the firſt office void,<note place="margin">12. Eliz. Dyer 2
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. Stat. E. 6. Cap. 8.</note> as if upon the <hi>diem,</hi> it be found that the land was holden of the King, <hi>ſed per quae ſervitia Iur. ignorant.</hi> And thereupon the, <hi>Melius</hi>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:93669:44"/>awarded, it is found that the tenure of a ſubject, and all other points uncertaine, as the Tenure, the State, the Value, &amp;c. the firſt office is void.</p>
            <p>When ſuch inqueſt is found for the King,<note place="margin">21. Ed. 3.2.</note> this finding is called an office, and it is a Title for the King, whereof the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt was taken of ſuch validity, that when the King is once ſeiſed by office, the ſeiſin, the office remaines till it bee diſcharged by matter of as high a nature as the office was,<note place="margin">1. H. 7.19.</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> matter of Record, namely a Livery, or <hi>Ouſter le maine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if an office found for a ſubject,<note place="margin">21. Ed. 3.2.</note> it makes no Title for him, but is and may be uſed, as matter of evidence to prove his Title.</p>
            <p>An office is ſufficient to entitle the King,<note place="margin">Stat. 1. H. 8. Ca. 8.3. H. 8. Ca. 22. Coo. 1. p.</note> although it be never returned, for if it doe appeare by the examination of the Eſcheator that hath upon ſuch office ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the lands into the Kings hands, it is ſufficient; But offices are uſually returned if they be found by Writ or Commiſſion into the Chancery whence the Writ or Commiſſion iſſued,<note place="margin">Alton Woods 42. Coo. 4. p. Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers caſe. 5.7. 18. El. ca. 12.</note> and from thence to the Clerkes of the Bagge tranſcripted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Exchequer, and into the Court of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:93669:44"/>Wards, but offices found <hi>Virtute officii,</hi> without any. Writ or Commiſſion, the Eſcheater may at his choice returne them either into the Chancery or Exchequer; And if they be found in the County Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine of Lancaſtar, Cheſter, or Durham, either by Writ or otherwiſe, they are to be thence tranſcripted into the Court of Wards.</p>
            <p>When an office is found inttiling the King to a Wardſhip,<note place="margin">16. Ed. 4.1. Coo. 4. p. Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers caſe. 59.</note> it relates to the time of the anceſtors death, and gives the King all the meane profits of his land for that time, becauſe the King hath the ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <hi>Ratione prioris tituli, viz.</hi> by reaſon of his ſeigniory, and loſeth his rent and ſervices in the meane time.</p>
            <p>But an office to entitle the King to an Ideot,<note place="margin">Coo. 8. p. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors caſe. 180.</note> relates for the meane profits and the land no further then the finding the office, becauſe the King hath the cuſtody of an Ideot, <hi>Jure protectionis Rege,</hi> prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction commeth by the office found, and not before; but yet for avoiding of mean conveiances of his land made by the Ide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot, the office hath relation to the Ideots Nativity.</p>
            <p>An office is requiſite to be found after
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:93669:45"/>the death of the Kings Tenant for two cauſes,<note place="margin">4. Eliz. Dyer 3: 1. H. 7.19. &amp;c. Coo. 9. P. Sir Geo. Reynolds caſe 95. b.</note> firſt for the dignity of the Kings perſon, who cannot take nor depart with any inheritance or freehold but by matter of record.</p>
            <p>Secondly becauſe it puts the King pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently upon the office found in actuall and full poſſeſſion of the Wards, lands, and the profits thereof ſince his Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors death before any ſervice or entrey by the Eſcheators, which actuall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion the King hath not before Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</p>
            <p>For although by <hi>Stamf.</hi> he hath before office poſſeſſion in law caſt upon him by right of his ſigniory,<note place="margin">Sum. prae. Rs. 54.69.</note> which he may by entry or ſeiſure of his Eſcheators before office reduce to an actuall poſſeſſion, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to enable him to keepe the lands in his owne hands, and to take the profits thereof, yet he hath not till office be found a perfect actuall poſſeſſion, ſuch as may enable him to grant or leaſe the land to his Committee.</p>
            <p>Becauſe the ſtatute of 18. <hi>H.</hi> 6. provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videth that all letters patents made by the King of lands or Ten:<note place="margin">Stat. 18. H. 6. C. b.</note> before of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice found and returned, or within one
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:93669:45"/>Moneth after, unleſſe it be to him that ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth his traverſe, the ſame office ſhall be voyd.</p>
            <p>But the Maſter of the Wards may within that moneth after office make a releaſe of Wards or Idiots lands to other then he that tenders a Traverſe being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled thereunto by the Stat.<note place="margin">Stat. 32. H. 8. Ca. 46.</note> 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. which is generall, and a latter Statute 18. <hi>Hen.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>This ſeemes to be the reaſon why our bookes ſay that in caſe of Wardſhip of land the King is preſently by the office in poſſeſſion before ſeiſure,<note place="margin">Coo. 1. p. Sir. Geo. Curſons ca. 956.</note> that hee hath not poſſeſſion till office, and that at this day the Eſcheator cannot ſeiſe any lands into the Kings hands for Wardſhip or other cauſe before the kings Title be firſt found by office,<note place="margin">1 H. 7 17. 4. H. 7.1. 5. Ed. 1. B. offic. 55.</note> which is to be underſtood to enable him by ſuch ſeiſure to grant the lands before office found,<note place="margin">Coo. 8. Paris Stoughtons caſe 169.</note> for to all other purpoſes it ſeemes not againſt law that the Eſcheator may at this day ſeiſe a Wards lands before office as the words of the <hi>diem</hi> directed him to doe, and as many bookes warrant, whereof ſee <hi>Stamf. Prae. Rs. fo.</hi> 12.14.78. b.</p>
            <p>But becauſe before office it is
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:93669:46"/>doubtfull whether the King have Title or no, the Eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hraters doe generally of their owne diſcretion ever ſince the Statute of Lincoine 79. <hi>E.</hi> 1. forbeare to ſeiſe before office, thereby to avoid the Kings great trouble in ſuing the <hi>Ouſter le maine,</hi> which he was driven to doe by the Eſcheators ſeiſure only, though afterwards the office found did not intitle the King.</p>
            <p>But the King as all other Lord,<note place="margin">20. Ed. 4 11. Stam. prae. Rs. 54.69.</note> that are common perſons, is in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Law preſently upon his Tenants death in poſſeſſion of the body of his Ward in right of his ſeigniory,<note place="margin">30. H. 6. Br. Patents 74. 11. Ed. 4.7.</note> and may grant away the Wardſhip thereof, before or after ſeiſure, and before office found, becauſe the ſaid Statute of 18. <hi>H.</hi> 6. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends not to the body, or in the anceſtors life time may grant it <hi>Quando event. &amp; de haered,</hi> as our bookes and common expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience agree.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:93669:46"/>
            <head>What words in Offices make a Tenure.</head>
            <head type="sub">See before Title Tenure.</head>
            <p>BUt by that which hath been ſaid it may be collected how great inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences may iſſue as well to the King by ſuppreſſing his Tenures, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly withdrawing one of his ancienteſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues of the Crowne as to his ſubjects, by finding the lands to be holden of the King, where in truth they are not, if cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption ſhould be uſed in the finding of offices, to prevent which, divers Statutes have been made under ſeverall penalties, concerning an upright and juſt demeanor therein, as well by the Kings Miniſters, as Jurors, and the parties whom it may concerue.</p>
            <p>The ſubſtance of moſt whereof follow,<note place="margin">34. Ed. 3. c. 19. 36. Ed. 3. c. 13. 8. H. 6. c. 16. 18. H. 6. c. 7.</note> All offices not found in good townes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly, and by men of good fame, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panelled by the Sheriffe, and having ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:93669:47"/>in the ſame Countie, and by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denture betweene the Eſcheator and the Jurours ſhall be voide.<note place="margin">33. H. 6.17. 33. H. 8.2.</note> Eſcheators ought to finde offices by vertue of writs within one moneth after the receipt thereof, and in good townes, and in open places; and ſhall take no fees therefore but 40. ſhillings for executing every writ.</p>
            <p>Eſcheators ought to bee men of 40. markes <hi>per annum</hi> at the leaſt,<note place="margin">1. H. 8.8.</note> except Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheators in Cities, Townes, and Counties Palatine of Lancaſter and Cheſter.</p>
            <p>Eſcheators or Commiſſioners ſhall not returne any office not found by the oathes of 12. men, and indented, and by them ſealed.</p>
            <p>Every man ſhall bee admitted by the Eſcheators, &amp;c. to give evidence openly in his preſence, at the finding of offices.</p>
            <p>Eſcheators, &amp;c. ought to receive offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces found by the Jury without delay, and to deliver, the Counterpart thereof inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſealed by himſelfe to the Jury, and the reſt with the foreman of the Jury, to the end that the Eſcheators may not imbeſill or change ſuch offices.<note place="margin">Stat. 8. H. 6. Ca. 16. 18. H. 6.7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>All offices are to bee returned in the Chancery or Exchequer within one
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:93669:47"/>Moneth after the taking thereof,<note place="margin">33. H. 8.22. Stat. 1. H. 8.8. 7. H. 8.2.</note> and the officers of the Chancery or Exchequer ought to receive the ſame, and to fill it within 3. or 4. dayes after receipt, and are thence to be tranſcripted into the Court of Wards, as above is ſet forth.</p>
            <p>Tenant for yeares, Copyholder,<note place="margin">Stat. 2. Ed. 6.8.</note> and he which hath a rent or other profit out of the Wards lands which are not found in the office, ſhall have and enjoy theſe, as if no ſuch office had beene found, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Statute he could not have.</p>
            <p>VVhere an heire of full age is by an office found to be under age, he may have his writ <hi>de aetate probanda,</hi> and may ſue his Livery or <hi>Ouſter le maine,</hi> and ſhall be reſtored to the profit of his land, ſo if the heire under age be found to be of leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer age then in truth he is, at his full age he may have like remedy, and ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to the profit of his lands from the time of his very full age, notwithſtanding ſuch untrue office.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
